Prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every day
life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind.
throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Greetings. Good evening, giant killers,
dragons, layers, stompers on scorpions and serpents.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host father, Stephen D. Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I am father, Andrew Stephen D.
Mac and E. Mayus, Pennsylvania.
If you're listening to us live, you can call us at 855 AF radio.
That's A552372346 and Matyska Trudy are very
own is taking your calls this evening and we're going to get to those in the second part of our show.
I take a deep breath to see if Father Stephen's going to interject something before I...
No, why would I do that? I don't know. So Lord of Spirits is brought to you by our listeners
and also by Chrysostom Academy. A lot of you listeners out there I know you work from home
and if you are telecommuting you can probably live almost anywhere. And if you're a parent of
of school-aged kids. You're like me.
working from a virtual office, then one of your big considerations for where you choose to live is where your kids go to school.
I love living in the Lehigh Valley of Pennsylvania. I've been here for 14 years now.
And part of why I love living here is because my kids go to Crisostom Academy, which is a Pantor Throx Classical School with Elementary through High School students.
It is a beautiful 55-acre campus that it's on, has very high academic standards, and it's
focused not just on educating the mind.
but actually forming the whole person in Christ.
So if you don't live here yet, think about moving
to the Lehigh Valley,
sending your kids to Chrysostom Academy.
And even if you don't telecommute,
our local economy is growing and it's producing jobs.
We've got eight orthodox parishes in our metro area.
So check out Chrysostomacademy.org
to see what I'm talking about.
So let me ask you this.
Do they ship the peps-
see there to put the peeps in it or do they ship the peeps somewhere to be put in the Pepsi?
Wow, I've, you know, I don't know.
But that reminds me, of course, of a, a, and this might seem weird to some people, but
I lived in North Carolina for 11 years.
And in North Carolina, they will, some of the people, especially out in the country, will,
will drink Pepsi and they will put salted peanuts in the top of that.
Do they do that in Louisiana?
I have never seen someone do that with Pepsi.
You can't.
You could barely get Pepsi products here, by the way.
If you prefer Pepsi in Texas or Louisiana, you are a pariah.
Interesting.
But I have seen people do the peanut thing with Mr. Pib.
Huh.
I've never tried that, but I will now consider it.
And Mr. Pib is great value doctor Pepper, by the way.
Right.
Like, didn't finish its degree.
That's why I said Mr. Pib.
Right.
Exactly.
It's ABD, which is not a thing.
you
So we're continuing our series,
Occurments of the Orthodox Church.
This is actually the ninth episode.
It's our longest-running series yet,
but where will it end?
Tears. It will end in tears.
Tonight, we're going to be talking about the Holy Mystery of Manasticism.
The actual service of making a monk is pretty brief, really.
And there's a lot, a lot of history that goes into that haircut.
So as is our want, we will be heading back in time,
but not to Dennis' this is time.
When does our time machine land this time?
Steven. In your second grade Sunday school class to destroy it. Buckle up. Yes. I do love
the two episodes. Yeah. A lot of people are going to be upset. Might burn their flanagraphs
in rage. Oh man, that takes me back. Yes. I love the flanagraph. Be careful environmentally
about burning a flantograph just for the record.
Someone just learned that the hard way.
So actually we're going back to numbers.
So we're not going to Genesis,
but we are going to the Torah.
Because if we're gonna talk about,
on our way to talking about
monastic, tancher, qua, sacrament,
or mystery of the church,
we're gonna talk about monasticism.
And if we're gonna talk about monasticism,
we have to start with old Testament monasticism,
which was a thing.
Indeed.
And I think the reason more people don't know it was a thing is that obviously our Protestant
friends, not to take a jab or anything, but our Protestant friends, the Therese toward
monasticism and toward a seticism, sort of the way we saw in the last episode.
episode with the way Puritans sort of reread the institution of monarchy in the Old Testament,
caused a reread of some of this. So we have to start here in the Old Testament with
right, vowed persons, persons who took vows, in some cases lifelong, which impacted their
lifestyle, their way of life, their behavior, and consisted of certain forms of
asceticism making it essentially the Old Testament precursor, the tradition out of which Christian
menasticism is going to evolve as we are going to see through the rest of this evening.
Indeed. And so the place where this is sort of first laid out in the Torah is in the book of
Numbers, as I mentioned, everybody's favorite book of the Bible. Oh, just right after Leviticus.
I don't know.
No, we should put up a poll.
Would you rather read Leviticus or numbers?
How interesting to see.
Yeah, because like I find Leviticus actually interesting.
Well, I'm a nerd.
Yeah.
I mean, you know, who isn't into exactly what you do with the fatty lobe that's on the
liver?
Yeah.
Whereas even I, the thing with the book of numbers is that it's inconsistent.
So there are sections of it that are intensely interesting.
Yeah.
and then other parts that are not.
Right. Big, big lists. Yeah. Yeah. Land allotments and yeah. Yeah. I mean, it kind of does what it says on the label.
But this is one of the interesting places I would argue that is important to understanding a lot of the rest of the scriptures.
Yeah. So this is numbers chapter six. And I'm going to read kind of a chunk. It's verses one through 21. But this is this is the key thing that we're
basing everything else that we're going to be saying. This is the beginning of all of that. And I think it's really
We're approaching holy weeks so get used to long scripture readings folks.
There we go.
Amen.
And I think we should especially note, I just want to pay attention to this, that the
first verse says the Lord spoke to Moses saying, so that means that what we're about to
read is directly from God.
So this is not a human institution that we're talking about.
This is directly from God.
So all right.
First one.
And the Lord spoke to Moses.
as saying, Speak to the people of Israel and say to them,
When either a man or a woman makes a special vow,
the vow of a Nazarite, To separate himself to the Lord.
He shall separate himself from wine and strong drink.
He shall drink no vinegar made from wine or strong drink,
And shall not drink any juice of grapes, or eat grapes, fresh or dried.
All the days of his separation, he shall eat nothing that is produced by the grapevine,
Not even the seeds or the skins.
the days of his vow, except the time is completed for which he's...
all the days that he separates himself to the Lord, he shall not go near a dead body,
not even for his father or his mother, for brother or sister. If they die,
shall he make himself unclean because his separation to God is on his head.
All the days of his separation, he is holy to the Lord.
And if any man dies very suddenly beside him and he defiles his consecrated head,
then he shall shave his head on the day of his cleansing. On the seventh day, he shall shave it.
On the eighth day he shall bring two turtle doves or two pigeons.
one for sin offering and the other for a burnt offering, and to make a tonement for him,
because he sinned by reason of the dead body. And he shall consecrate his head on that same day,
and separate himself to the Lord for the days of his separation, and bring a male lamb a year old
for a guilt offering. But the previous period shall be void because his separation was defiled.
And this is the law for the Nazarete, when the time of his separation has been completed. He
should be brought to the entrance to the tent of meeting, and he shall bring his gift to the Lord,
one male lamb a year old
old without blemish for burnt offering, and one you lamb a year old without blemish
as a sin offering, and one ram without blemish as a peace offering, and a basket of unleavened
bread loaves of fine flour mixed with oil and unleavened wafers smeared with oil and
their grain offering and their drink offerings.
And the priest to bring them before the Lord and offer his sin offering and his burnt offering.
And he shall offer the ram as a sacrifice of peace offering to the Lord with the basket
of unleavened bread.
The priest shall offer also its grain offering and its drink offering.
And the Nazarene shall save his consecrated head at the entrance of the tent of meeting,
and shall take the hair from his consecrated head and put it on the fire that is under
the sacrifice of the peace offering.
And the priests shall take the shoulder of the ram when it is boiled and one unlemied
loaf out of the basket and one unlemied wafer, and shall put them on the hands of the
Nazarene after he has saved the hair of his consecration, and the priests shall waive
them for a waive offering before the Lord.
They are a holy portion for the priest.
together with the breast that is waived and the thigh that is contributed. And after that,
the Nazarite may drink wine. This is the law of the Nazarite. But if we vows and offering
to the Lord above his Nazarite vow, as he can afford, in exact accordance with the
vow that he takes, then he shall do in addition to the law of the Nazarite.
So that's the passage. No grapes, no raisins, no raisins.
I know that's what it says just plain brand flakes
Not even one scoop let alone two scoops.
That's just weedy's now.
It's just weedy's sort of.
I don't know.
So, yeah, so this is the institution of the Nazarite Val.
Now to sort of, I know that was sort of the biblical info dump, but now to sort of work
through that a little.
Yes.
And talk about a little more.
Bye.
Nazarai is pretty clearly derived from the Hebrew Nazir.
I mean, pretty obviously, which means to set apart
or to make holy as a verb.
And of course, being made holy means being set apart,
we've talked about that before, right?
That's the concept, right?
So this is a person who is setting themselves apart
to be holy to God.
the Greek
translations of the Old Testament are sort of all over the place with Nazareth.
So, in some places, it gets translated, usually as either the sanctified one or the vowed
one, the one who has taken a vow, right, for obvious reasons, both of those would apply.
Some places it's not translated, it's just translated as Nazir in Greek characters.
and Greek characters.
So that's fairly clear cut.
So sorry, Father Andrew, you don't get to do much with pedomologies on it.
It's okay.
I can't win them all.
So and then, right, during the period of this vow, right, you've got these three main
rules and you could hear how strictly they're in force, right?
there's this no wine and strong drink.
but that's enforced so strictly that like vinegar,
a grape skin, right?
Grape seed.
No seeds, no raisins, no grapes.
Like you can't come near it, right?
Yeah.
So this is, right, when you are one of these vowed people,
then there's no legal, like sometimes we're in the land,
Right, so sometimes we...
we get a bit legalistic with the fasting rules and orthodox people, right? And we're like,
well, you know, technically, there's no room for that kind of legalism here, right? This is just
anywhere, you know, someone throws a grape at you, you have to dodge it, right? Like no,
right, room for messing around. You also have the no cutting, no cutting of the hair.
Yeah, although you have to do a head reset first,
like you have to shave it all off,
and then let it grow out so that all the hair you have
during that period is the hair of your consecration.
Right, yeah.
And that kind of ritual appears in a couple other places
in the Torah, probably the most notable one
is in Deuteronomy.
if a man wants to make a woman take it
war to be his wife, who's not therefore not an Israelite, right? He's not allowed to take her as
a slave or a concubine, right? But he can marry her. And in that instance, she also shapes her head
at that point. And so this signifies sort of making a new beginning or a new commitment, right?
And of course, that happens on both sides of the vow.
Yeah, right it happens as you begin the vow and then it happens
is the vow ends where you make this sort of new beginning. Yeah.
Those are like locks of love or you know one of those things to donate.
We donate it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I will also point out for the record. I find that with this
and we're going to be talking about Samson later. Everyone always assumes
that all these Hebrew folks had long straight hair.
right? This is not the case. Right? Right. They had so I don't know what you would call
it, but yes, the hair often is curly and kind of you know what you call it. You just don't
want to say it live on the outward. It makes your faith ready. No, no, I mean, there's no,
there's the there's the well see so I used to know a guy when I so when I was in college,
I knew a guy who is wider than I am and I'm I mean, I'm pretty white. And but he had
this kind of fluffy curly hair and when you grow it.
It grew up and he referred to it as an Anglo.
Oh, and yeah.
So I, but I don't know, you know, what the ancient Near East, what the term, I can't even,
I just, yeah.
So some of these folks growing their hair out, they would have looked more like a basketball
player in the 1970s, right?
There you go.
Then, then like Fabio, right?
Right.
So don't assume, right?
And, and for men, notice it's, it's hair in the head.
That included the beard, by the way.
Oh.
ah
Yeah, not just the top of the head, but the whole head.
Yeah.
What about eyebrows?
They shape off the eyebrows, too.
This I do not know.
I do not think so.
No hairs.
Given the shaving technology they had,
although the Egyptians did it.
But yeah.
So and then the third rule, which again,
you can see how rigorously it's enforced is no corpses.
Yeah, right.
Even if it's a family member.
Yeah.
or next.
someone drops dead next to you.
Yeah, you have to like jump away.
Yeah.
And it's interesting how like if you, with that right, if the, if someone drops dead next
to you, then you have to go and offer sacrifices.
And then you have to reset.
Like it doesn't, you're tiny all over.
Yeah, you have to start all over.
It doesn't count for the vow.
And this is if you look in later, uh, Jewish rabbinic literature about this.
right? There's no lessening of the
strictness, right? Like it says a
Nazarite cannot be in a house with a
dead body. A Nazarite cannot end in
the shade of a tree because there
might be a dead body buried under
the tree. Amazing. Right. So like
the level to which you're not allowed
to come near a corpse. It's also
interesting. One of the reasons we
know that this didn't just include
human corpses, right?
But corpses in general is not only just that you know the corpses of animals were also considered ceremonial on clean and the Torah, right?
I mean
but
Is that the actual words that are used here in Hebrew are an effe schmote. It literally means dead souls
Oh, wow
So if you want someone to take these dreams away that point you to another day
You're out of luck if you're an Azarite because you can't go near
Dead Souls.
Father Andrews pretending he got that reference.
But it's okay.
I don't need to get every reference.
Someone did and that person is one of my people.
So there are, as we noted, right?
And as right when it starts, this is something a lot of folks don't realize either.
both men and women could become Nazarites.
taken Nazareille vow. Yeah. The prominent example, well, not just the
prominent examples, all the examples that we have in the scriptures proper. Now,
if you go to Jewish tradition about different people who took Nazareille
vows, there are women. But in scripture, all the cases we have are men who
take Nazareille vows. Right. But either men or women could do this. Right? This is
another connection to later.
monasticism, right? And there were both temporary and lifelong Nazarets.
So there were people who were dedicated either by themselves early in their life to be
Nazarets for their whole lives or by their parents. The parent could dedicate someone to be a Nazarete.
Now, in later rabbinic literature, there is a right of refusal.
What's the child comes of age?
Yeah.
Right.
So that would be in modern terms when you get par mitzvahd, right?
If you could leave the Nazarite thing.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm thinking about that now, right?
Life long Nazarite.
Okay.
It's one thing, you know, no grapes, no dead bodies.
But like, never, ever cutting that hair.
Yeah.
Yeah, I remember who's that
singer, that country singer that had that's incredibly.
Crystal Gale.
That's her.
That's her right.
She was big in the 70s and 80s.
Her hair was like down to her ankles.
Yeah.
Maybe she was a Nazarite.
I'm just putting that out there.
I'd like to check if she ever had any grape juice.
Yes.
There's a bunch of people typing into Google right now.
Was Crystal Gale a Nazarite?
And it's just going to mess with the algorithm unbelievably.
I'm here for it.
Um.
So, if it's a temporary vow, right, then the text we heard from numbers describes the sacrifices
that were made at the end of it.
So, it lists a sin offering, a peace offering, and a whole-burned offering.
But then in the context of the peace offering, it also mentions bringing a grain offering
and a drink offering, right?
So it's sort of everything.
Right, it's sort of the whole slate, right, of offerings that you bring at the end of the vow.
And then added to all of those offerings to God, quite literally, because it's thrown into the fire of the peace offering,
is all the hair that you grew during the vow.
Right, that is thrown in and burnt.
And I know we've talked about before back when we did the episodes on Sacrifice.
And I think we probably touched on this in the baptism episode as well, that in animal sacrifices,
in the ancient Near East, including in ancient Greece, one of the last stages before an animal
was sacrificed would be cutting off a tuft of its hair and throwing it into a fire, usually a bowl
where incense was being burned, right, or some other nearby fire.
and that was sort of the beginning of the offering of the animal.
And that is one of the actions, the sacrificial actions
that in Greek and Roman sacrificial ritual
abraded and emphasized to try to make it so that the animal
is offering itself, that you're not killing the animal,
that the animal is offering itself to the gods
and you're just sort of facilitating things.
But that's important because...
Right. The context here is it's not that God really likes the smell of burning hair because I mean who does right?
And you know, I
Have never gotten through a lantern holy week the Orthodox Church without smelling it at some point
You know when one of my classmates was ordained to the deaconate
I'm not going to mention his name
But I don't want to shame the poor guy. He is now a fine-upstanding priest and has been for many years
But when he was ordained to the deaconate
He was serving as a subdeacon at our common alma mater of St. T. Consuminary and
He had you know decent he had a decent hair, you know, he had he had hair and he was serving as a subdeacon
And he was holding up a candle in front of him and the front of his hair lit on fire
during that service and
We called him the pyrodeacon for some months
following the father pyrodeacon
So well there's a period of my life.
And holy week, I would be holding an icon.
People would come by holding candles and venerate said icon.
And I went over the course of the evening,
have all the hair burned off the back of my right hand.
Yeah.
And I am hairy like an ape or some sort of goat man on the back of my hand.
Can confirm.
And so this was quite accurate.
So he said, but so yes, that is not a pleasant smell.
That's not what we're going.
for here. This isn't part of the pleasing aroma of sacrifice thing. This is a self offering.
Right. Right. This is to symbolize the person offering them self to God along with the sacrifices
by offering a part of themselves in place of the whole. So when when a Nazarete vow was taken
temporarily, right, when it was not a lifelong thing but was a temporary thing. I'm going to do this
further.
six months or a year, however long. The idea was that this was what might be called
a conditional vow meaning you would take this vow either because there was something
in particular you were praying for or you would sort of make the vow in advance. You would
say you would be praying for something, right? You'd be praying safe for a family members
healing and you would vow to God.
You know if if you heal this person I will you know take the Nazarete vow for a year
Right, and then you would fulfill that vow as part of that right so you're gonna spend the year that you're
living as a Nazarete
praying about that thing and or repenting of that thing
Yeah, sort of a dedication as it were right and so
So that is...
is sort of tightly tied in with then why you're offering these sacrifices at the end of
it. Right? That sort of the culmination, right, of the vow itself, which is a sort of
sacrifice. So now, give a trigger warning. We haven't given a trigger warning in a while.
Yes.
not a parental warning though.
No, not a parental...
warning. Yeah. Might could be. But no, this is not a parental warning. This is this is a trigger
word that there are a lot of people who get deeply. Which I talk about Samson. I know I shouldn't say
it's funny, but it's funny like odd to me. I don't know. Yeah. Straight. Yeah. Right. This of all
things like this is this is where people just yeah. I think it's because people look at him as some
kind of superhero Samson's right this is my
very, especially little boys, you go to Sunday school, you learn about
Samson, he seems really cool and awesome, right?
He's like an action hero, right?
So we're gonna have some real talk.
I'm gonna ruin a lot of Sunday school.
Talk about Samson.
It turns out that Samson is a very bad monk.
Anyway, all the eliteration.
Yeah.
So yeah, so be prepared.
Right. We're about to say a bunch of things about Samson that are that are not positive.
When we get to the end, we're explaining that none of the non-positive are original to us.
No. Right. Literally most of it is just what's in the Bible.
Right. So it's what the scriptures say about Samson. It's what church fathers say about Samson.
And it's right, that's really what we're talking about here.
Yep.
Yep. So, well, let's start talking about this.
Most people will get upset. Yes. So, before we could really dig into Samson himself, right?
We have to set the stage a little because when the story of Samson begins with the announcement
of Samson's birth, Samson is probably the most famous Nazarite in the Bible, right?
Like, if somebody says, who's the Nazarite in the Bible, and you can come up with anybody,
Samson's probably the first guy you say, right?
They remember the hair thing. Yeah. So when that story starts of his birth, right, right off the
bat it talks about the angel of the Lord coming to that doesn't mean a lot to us. Right. As modern people,
right, even if we're fairly biblically illiterate, right, we know, well, okay, Dan is one of the 12
tribes, it's one of the northern tribes that got destroyed.
when the Northern Kingdom of Israel got destroyed by the Assyrians.
So they vanished off the face of the earth.
The name, a lot about this tribe.
But the original readers of the Book of Judges, they knew all about Dan.
Dan has a certain reputation.
And a lot of this is coming out of Torah.
So the Torah establishes a certain character for the tribe of Dan.
We see that.
play out in Joshua in judges, right? And so even when the story of Samson starts and we find out,
oh, this is a dude from Dan, right? That's a tip off, right? It's already setting the stage.
Is the baddest part of town? Yeah. And you're the the meanest man. Right. In the whole town. Right.
Yeah, it's worse than that though.
Yes.
Yeah.
right? There's not, you know, 20th century Germans or see, right? There's not going to
be like happy kids. There's not going to be a romantic comedy, right? Then unfolds after
that, right? Right. Yes. So the first thing we need to know about Dan historically, right?
So we've mentioned before on the show.
And we're not going to go through all the biblical stuff starting in the Torah about this
again, but that ancient Israel was not unified in a genetic way.
Yeah, it was a collection of different groups of people who all lived the same way.
Right.
And even coming out of Egypt, right, we've talked about how there were people there who were
ethnically things other than Hebrew.
Right, there were people who were literally biologically descended from Abraham.
There were people who had married into Abrahamite tribes and clans.
And there were people who were just sort of adopted and assimilated into
clans and tribes within Israel. Right.
And we gave it the time.
One of the very prominent examples is Caleb, right, who's the big hero, along with Joshua,
who starts out as a Canaanite, a Kenisite, to be specific, and ends up being an
it out.
of the tribe of Judah. Right? And his father appears who is a Kenisite, right? So he is not
biologically descended from Judah. Nevertheless, he ends his life as an elder, one of the clan heads
in the tribe of Judah. Yeah. So Dan is like this. Yes. Dan is one of two tribes, Dan and
And I mean, now we should say Dan himself as a person, as a son of...
Jacob slash Israel there is a son one of his sons is named Dan. Yeah, right. Yeah. Yeah. But these
people are not mostly even descended from him. Right. Dan and Gator the two tribes that are mostly
assimilated from other people who have become the most of their people have become part of Israel
but are not most of the humans are not biologically descended from Abraham.
By our standards right they didn't think that way as we've talked about before in the ancient world
They didn't know what DNA was
They didn't have heredity tests, right you were a member of a tribe based on being a member of a clan being based on being a member of a family in that clan in that tribe, right
It didn't matter right so we talked about Phineas who had a different skin color for most of the Israelites, right? Yeah, we came the high priest
so
This isn't a huge problem. It's there in the Torah to find. We will go through all of it now
but in particular
most of the Danites
became part of Israel after originally being one of the sea peoples
So the sea peoples were agruded within the territory of Egypt some of them the most prominent ones being the Philistines
settled in the Levant right
but so most of the Danites are biologically descended from those resettentling
sea peoples who by the way they originally came from Greece. Yeah. We've also
talked before about how this weird thing starting in the Torah, starting in
Deuteronomy, but can through like first Maccabees and stuff that at least some
of the Greeks were said to be descended from Abraham, and that's because of this,
Yes, because...
there were people who were what we would call ethnic Greeks today, get it's an
achronistic, but what we would call ethnic Greeks, there were people of that
extraction who were part of Israel. Right. Right. Because they lived the life. Yeah.
Well, as we'll find out about them, kind of they were supposed to. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
Some of them get flushed back out of Israel.
But so that's where the Danics sort of come from.
Right?
And sort of the first clue that there's something going on with Dan is not about the later
tribe, well, not directly.
It is ultimately about the later tribe.
But it is part of a prophecy that's given in the testament of Jacob.
So in Genesis 48, Jacob blesses Joseph's sons in Genesis 49.
before he dies, Jacob blesses his own 12 sons. That includes Dan in...
Well, as one of the tribes of Israel doing okay so far. Dan shall be a serpent in the way
of Viper by the path that bites the horses' heels so that his rider falls backward.
Yeah. Yeah, so that's not good. Like, thanks, Dad. We called a snake, right?
Imagine that. Your dad is dying and this is his last word. He calls you a pit Viper.
Yeah, and we have to take the context too.
This is the second of the last chapter of Genesis.
Think about the third chapter of Genesis at the serpent there, right?
Yeah, right.
So this is saying, Hey, Dan's going to be bad.
Now, this isn't talking about the guy, his son who's standing there.
This is talking about the tribes just like if you read the prophecy about Judah,
which we will at great vespers before Palm Sunday.
Clue.
Right.
The, it's all about the Messiah, the future king of Israel being descended from Judah,
not about Judah the person who was not a king himself.
So yeah, this is a tip off.
Dan is not going to win a prize for being the most faithful tribe quite the opposite.
And so then when we're, as we mentioned, talking about the book of numbers,
as the tribes of Israel are entering into the land of Canaan,
each tribe was given a land allotment that they were supposed to go and take
and get rid of the giant clans that were there and take this land and settle there
and that was going to be granted to them sort of as a permanent land grant,
the whole
economic system laid out by the Torah.
That's the way the whole thing is supposed to work.
Yeah, so what happens is that Dan is given a particular piece of land just as all the
tribes are, but they lose it and they decide to go in their ancestor.
So they took this out of the piece of land and then they even renamed it to be Dan.
Like, no, this is our place.
Yes.
Well, not just a piece of land, a city.
Yeah.
the thing came built. Right. So it's not just that they didn't go get the land God gave them to take.
It's that they're rejecting that sort of agrarian way of life, right? This is
in the context of someone who's just read Genesis, right? And the rest of the Torah and now you're
in Joshua, right? Oh no, we don't want that land to go work it and farm it. We want this city. And
And so we're going to go and massacre everyone there and take it for ourselves.
Yeah.
And so, by the way, before we get too far because I forgot to mention this, the DNA in
Homer, same people.
Oh, okay.
That's the same people.
So, but it's not just the fact that they massacred everyone.
in this city and took it for themselves. Part of it also is where this city is located.
This city happens to be at the foot of Mount Hermann.
Yes. See several episodes of this program.
If you don't know what we're talking about, we'll just say it has something to do with bail.
Yeah, there's a dark evil stuff and right gateways to the underworld and yeah, it's right near pain
Sir Banius, right, the spring with the pagan worship, right? So not far from not too far from
Bishan, right? So, so it isn't just a question of urban life versus rural agricultural life.
It's they're choosing to essentially displace and replace the Canaanites, but then just be Canaanites,
Right, is the idea here.
That's further emphasized later in judges, right? This story is briefly
retold in in judges chapter 18, but also there's this kind of wonky story.
So everybody, when you're in Sunday's Scop with Samson, yeah, because after
Samson, the story in 17 and 18 gets weird. And then in 1920, it gets like, it
turns into like an Eli Roth movie like it's just
We're like disturbing and weird.
But chapter 18 tells this story about how the fighting men of Dan who are going around
raiding again, we're not out farming.
We're out taking through violence from the neighbors.
And they go and steal an ephod that's being worshipped in some idols.
the lever.
who is serving them? Yeah, what I down and take it back to Dan to set up Dan's new state
religion around this idol. Right. So all that, right, when we find out Samson is from the tribe of Dan,
right? This doesn't bode well, right? And there's nothing that
happens later in the Scriptures to kind of fix Dan's reputation.
There's no one who comes out of Dan and sort of redeems it.
And the old even Mount Hermann gets redeemed.
Yeah, you know, but but not not Dan.
Yeah. So not all are they are they wiped out by the Assyrians, but yeah.
So are the other or the ten tribes, right?
Yeah.
But when you get all the way to the book of Revelation,
all the way at the end of the Bible.
Revelation 7 verses 4 through 8.
This is the 144,000 sealed.
12,000 for each of the 12 tribes.
If you read that list of tribes carefully,
you'll notice something.
Dan's not...
It references to the half tribe of Manasseh
and the half tribe of Ephraim.
Because there are these sons.
Yeah, the two sons of Joseph, right.
So Joseph is the 12th son, or the 11th, actually, right?
Benz is essentially these two half-tribes.
in this list revelation get promoted to being full tribes. So there's still 12. Yeah.
To make up for Dan being booted out. So yeah. So all of those prophecies about Israel,
about Ephraim, about the northern kingdom being reconstituted and redeemed that we've talked
about before on the show that get made in the, by the Hebrew prophets. None of that apparently
includes Dan.
Right.
So, Dan is the one left out.
So start to finish.
This does not bode well for the Samson story we're about to hear.
And sort of the urlayer of stories of Heracles.
A.K.A. Hercules.
Right.
I say Heracles very obvious right off the jump.
Element that looks similar.
and some IGN stables or...
Hydra, no.
A little less though, right?
But the D.V.L.I. jumps out, but there are other things too.
There are other things.
The stuff with the foxes.
There's a whole thing about this, right?
And so, this is another one of those places, right,
where you see influence of ancient Near Eastern stories
outside of Israel on how stories are told.
within the Scriptures.
Yeah, we're not using that language very deliberately.
Yeah, yeah, we're not saying, you know,
like we're saying that this didn't really happen
or that it's actually a pagan story,
but, but rather, as you said,
the way that the story is told.
Right, the way that the story is told.
And you can see why you might choose Heracles in particular
given the origin of the Danite people,
that these are stories that still would have resonated.
with them. Right. And so part of what's going on here is again, not saying things are being
fictionalized, but you could tell a story using language and using imagery that will cause
you to think of it in terms of another story. Yeah. Yep. Right. That you are familiar with.
Yep. Right. And you see this all the time. Well, hey, here's a really on the nose example.
the lie in the witch of the wardrobe.
Okay.
Right. You're telling a story about a talking lion, but it's a little reminiscent of another
story in the Bible.
Just a scotch, right?
Right.
So, you can tell a story of that way, and it's not just a fictional story like the
lie of the Witch of the Wardrobe.
You can tell a true story in a way that makes someone sound Christ-like, for example.
Right, I could I could tell the
story of someone's death in a way where I'm trying to convey this person was really laying
down their life for their friends.
Yeah, there you go.
Right?
Or you could tell the same story without, you know, without lying and just tell it as,
oh, this horrible tragedy of how this person died, right?
Like, you could shape how you tell a story to make a particular point, to be reminiscent
of other stories, to create different things.
And so that's part of what's going on here.
that Samson's story is being told in a way that is trying to, as we've seen with so many times
where some story gets remixed or turned around or shifted slightly or imagery gets reused in
the Old Testament, to kind of invert that story. The story. And in this case, you're taking
a story which presented Herically. Right. One of the mighty men of Old, the men of renowned,
who was presented in the
this heroic figure, right? And you're presenting them as a non-heroic figure. Not to say again,
Samson is Hercules, but to say no, that kind of figure is not a heroic figure.
Samson presented to us as Hercules. He's the Christian Hercules.
As Christian or Jewish Hercules, right? Where they took the story and shaped it even more,
To be like the story of Hercules, including trying to make samples.
So yeah, yeah, we're not gonna be doing that this evening again.
Honestly, sorry, not sorry if you're triggered.
So that brings us with this background.
Right, this brings us to Judges 13 in the story of Samson's birth.
Yeah, so we know it's in the Dan area, but it's near a particular town.
Yes.
It's named Beth Shemish.
Yeah, Beth.
Shemesh is how it's usually done and it can also be used for a temple.
So it could just be the temple of Shemesh, Shemesh being the pagan sun god.
Just like Bethel, the house of God.
Right.
Because God is in this place as Jacob said.
So this is the house of the pagan sun god, Shemesh, who we've talked about was
major figure, the Babylonian pantheon, but also was a
particular hypostasis of Shemish was worshiped in Jerusalem before David took it.
Shemish said a car.
So that's also a truck tip off, Dan,
living near a temple of a pagan god.
And now even though this is gonna be
this miraculous birth where this is an elderly barren couple. We see this a lot in the scriptures.
So this is a setup we're going to see. Elderly, barren couple, the angel of the Lord comes to them.
See the angel of the Lord episode says, you are going to have a son and is
It's very specific.
This is Yahweh, the God of Israel,
is going to give you this son.
Miraculously give you this son,
even though you are an older barren couple.
And when he's born, they name him,
Shema Shone.
They name him after Shema Sh, the pagan God.
What are you thinking?
Yes.
I mean, like I think from most of us,
name.
have a big impact, right? But like imagine, you know, imagine, you know, the Archangel Gabriel
comes to the Virgin Mary and says, you're going to bear a son and she and she decides to name him Zeus.
Yeah. That's the kind of ridiculousness that this that this is. Yes, the cluelessness.
Yeah. Right. And even within the narrative in judges 13, right, where Manoa,
Samson's father is talking to the angel of the Lord.
Manoa keeps trying to get the...
angel of the Lord, like as two independent beings. Right? And lest you say, based our episode,
well, if this is Christ, right, then well, sort of, you know, try and find some way around it.
He explicitly says, but no, explicitly says in judges 13 verse 8, that he thinks the angel of
of the Lord is a human.
So he's trying to worship Yahweh, the God of Israel, and the human who he thinks Yahweh
sent as a prophet to tell him this.
Yeah, so he's like he's some kind of God king kind of figure.
It's how he treats him.
Right.
Also, kind of a pagan thing to do.
Also notice the angel of Yahweh, the angel of the Lord here is presenting himself as a man.
So, but part of this and now that setup right tells us okay parents are clueless right this this probably isn't gonna go well
Right this kid isn't gonna get raised up at the fear of the Lord shall we say
But what they're told is that God is commanded 13 verse 5 that he's gonna be a Nazareth from birth for life
Yeah, so this one set aside for these purposes right
So he's gonna be set aside as a
Holy person.
Yeah.
So remember the three vows everybody, because this is important.
No wine or anything grape-like or grape related.
Grape adjacent.
Yeah, I think grape adjacent.
You got to, you know, the hair is not to be cut during the period of the vow.
Of course with the, with Samsung, that's going to be the whole life.
And no dead bodies.
Don't go near any dead bodies.
Don't even imagine the same houses of dead body, no dead bodies.
So these are the three key things for the Nazarite vows.
Yeah, so does he do any does he does he successfully lived this way and those are the specific rules but also in general right?
Remember this is a holy set apart person. Right. He's basically Yahweh the God of Israel.
Even though he's named after Shhh. Yeah, I mean imagine you know God you know God comes to your parents and says this one is going to become a monk or a nun from birth
and that's gonna be the life that they live like we have seen lives like this.
Well, there's a number of them like this, like two books later, Samuel.
Yeah, right exactly.
Exactly.
Yes.
But there's a contrast, shall we say?
Right.
So, how does he do?
Well, not great.
So right off the jump, the first thing we see is the
fuck
his parents to go marry a Philistine woman. Right, which is not against the Nazaride
vow, but is against the Torah in general. So it's as a sad he's deliberately disobeying
his parents disobeying his parents. Yeah, right. To go and do this and not really acting
holy instead of part, shall we say. So he goes, he marries this woman, he then leaves
and uh
The text literally says that later on he comes back and decides he want, like after a long time,
he comes back and says he wants to sleep with her.
And her father says, man, you took off. I thought you hated her. I thought you didn't want her.
So I married her off to somebody else. Somebody else. Right.
And then, you know, Samson gets mad and takes revenge.
It would do, right?
Yes.
And so we also then have this episode of him tearing the lion in half, right?
We could argue whether actually killing an animal constitutes coming into contacts with
the court, contact with the corpse because he's making a corpse, right?
But what you can't argue with is that then on the way back, he finds the corpse of said
lion and eats honey out of it.
which I think everybody finds...
little charming because the whole, you know, riddle that he does later, right? Yeah. But still,
no, no, no corpses. Like, this is one of the three things you vow. Yeah. There is no one listening
to this program right now, who, if they were on fear factor, and they had to eat honey out of a
three-day-old lion carcass would be able to do it. Tough but fair. So, but so that's,
There's one valve broken.
Right.
Hanging around the corpse, eating out of a corpse.
And then of course, he's going to pick up the jawbone of a donkey and kill a bunch of
people with it.
There's another corpse.
Right.
Yep.
So then, you know, prostitute.
And then, I think it's Nazarite would, right?
Yes.
And then it goes, it starts sleeping with the lila.
Yeah.
And the reason we're pointing to the sexual sin again is not because it's explicitly
not a Nasirite but we're gonna see this is
going to become important later. Literally, this is going to become important later.
Samson's bad example sexually. It's going to become important later in the history of Christian
monasticism. Yeah. To just hold on to that thought, everybody. He goes, he gets drunk at a wedding
feast, right? So there goes the wine thing. Yep. And so then finally, when he loses his strength,
when he gets taken as a slave, when he gets his eyes gouged out and all this.
It's when he lets, you know, let's on about his hair getting cut and his hair gets cut.
Why then?
Ours.
Yeah.
It's not that there's some kind of magical strength in the hair.
Despite what he may have said to people, right?
Yes.
Like you like, like, why do you believe this guy?
Why would you believe what he says to, you know, to, uh, to Delilah, you know, like that's
right.
Yeah.
It's that that's breaking the his fight.
Now he's broken all the vows.
Right. So what's the last valve's broken? He loses his,
loses his strength, take a prisoner, eyes gouged out. And so then we have this final scene, sexual activity going on.
There's drunkenness going on. All this is going on. He gets between the two pillars and does not repent.
If you don't believe me, go read what he says.
Yeah, he doesn't say I'm sorry God or I have I have sinned in your
or any of the kind of, I'm repenting kind of language you get in the Bible.
Right. He says, God, give me my strength back one last time so I can get revenge for my eyes.
Yeah. Which God does give him strength, right? But that doesn't mean that he's a repentant guy.
Yeah. And like there's even the line in one point where I says the Holy Spirit rushed upon him,
which is not the same language as being filled with the Holy Spirit. This is...
you know what we call Holy Spirit possession or where God just kind of takes control of somebody and
takes out do something. Right. And so his last words are let me die with the Philistines.
Yeah. The judges 60 verse 30. So he literally uses this last verse of strength for murder suicide.
Like in a good Nazarete would do. So what happens over the course of the book of judges is that
that the judges getting, so it's not just...
There's the on one level, there's this cycle, right?
Israel falls into sin.
God brings usually a foreign oppressor, right?
To come and oppress Israel.
It will cries out to God.
Says we repent, we'll do better, deliver us.
God raises up a judge to set things right.
Rinse and repeat, right?
Yeah, so many things.
Samson gets used by God to sit
things right, but in spite of himself, right, lot, but it's not just a cycle. It's a downward spiral.
Yeah. The judges get increasingly worse. They get increasingly more shifty. Right. The first couple
of the old shamgar are presented as being fine, right? It's being just men of God with no issues.
Right, not a lot of people naming a-
It's Shamgar, I've noticed.
No.
And if you did, right, it wouldn't be one of those situations
where it's like, oh, well, your Shamgar B
and your Shamgar D, right?
And they're kindergarten class, right?
That's right.
You're gonna be the only Shamgar.
Yeah.
They're gonna have to hear some jokes.
Shamwau, right?
Some stuff like that.
But that's gonna happen anyway.
Kids will find something to make fun of your kid about.
Just name him Shamgar.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
Um.
But.
But by the time you get to Gideon, Gideon is a fairly shifty character.
Right. There are these different things.
Like there's the whole episode, which I did...
I think you need to know a little bit of Hebrew to understand what's going on,
because they come and they keep accusing him of trying to make himself the king of Israel.
And he keeps saying, no, no, I'm not doing that. Why would you say that?
Okay, right.
So...
I know it. Yep.
Yes.
So, getting it keeps doing sort of shift.
stuff like that. So you're going, okay, well, not ideal dude, but he got the job done
with the Midianites. That is issues. But you have the whole thing with the EFA that becomes
a snare for it. So that great. By the time you get to the last judge in the book of judges
here. The last individual judge of Samson, things have gotten really bad.
right? Because judges is an extended case for why Israel needs in particular the
Davidic monarchy. Yeah, because I mean there's all these references to the time of the judges
being the time when everyone did what it was right and there was no king in Israel.
Right. And there was no king in Israel. Just in case you were thinking Saul was the guy,
right, the benchmarks get put through the ringer in the last couple. So yeah, so Samson is
here at the bottom of this, right? So that...
The theme of this story is that even when you have someone like Samson from a tribe like Dan,
God will still deliver his people, sort of in spite of themselves. That's the theme here.
So that was, as I mentioned, there are probably triggered people out there. Our phone lines may be
filling up. I know there are there are in fact people not making this up there are in fact
people who refer to him as Saint Samson. And we should say there are there is
saints, saints, there's two there's St. Samson the hospital and there's
Saint Samson of Dole, D-O-L. Those are both saints that are named Samson.
Yes, but this guy is not one of them.
No, we're gonna explain to you exactly why that's the case now.
Yes, if the four, if the one we just talked about, yes, isn't enough.
So if just reading the story of Samson in the Bible
I Tis a D-
enough for you. Yeah. Cause you think the Bible's a magic riddle box. Yeah, we're literally
interpret where it literally does not say a single good thing that he ever did. Yes. Yeah.
Um, right. So there's only there's only one other place in the Bible where Samson gets
sort of explicitly mentioned. Uh, and that of course is in Hebrews 11, right. So I know
some of the folks out there who are starting to get upset about me saying negative things
about that.
They will look here, St. Paul and Hebrews says, well, time fails to speak of big, long list of people
on which Samson occurs. Right. Right. When he's talking about faith, right. There's a basic problems
with this. Right. The most obvious being we don't know what St. Paul actually would have set. Yeah,
he just says, I don't have time to talk about this big list of people. Yeah, that's all it says in
in the verse 32. Right? He's got to work his way through the Bible. Right?
And he just names like the next, he goes through like the people of the book of judges in order.
Yeah, he doesn't know what he said.
And then he mentions Daniel, David and Samuel and the prophets and then says, you know,
who through faith, conquer kingdoms of force, judges, obtain promises, stop the mouths of
lines. But like none of the good things that are mentioned in there actually apply to
Samson. Right. Right. You know, and so you can't assume that, right. Samson was not
on in two. Right. So and if you look at some of the other people on the list. Right.
So for example, he mentions barrack. Well, if you've read the book of judges,
you know that what happens with barrack is barrack is chosen to be the judge of Israel,
but is kind of a wimp. And so God raises up Deborah, the prophetess,
right, and jail another woman to sort of do the job, right? And the whole idea here is the fact
that God raised up these women.
And to do it is supposed to shame Barak for being a man and not doing what he was supposed
to do.
Yeah.
Right.
God sends a woman to do a man's job.
That's it.
They do it better than Barak did.
Right.
Yeah.
And one of the other people is Jeff, it seems very likely sacrificed his actual daughter.
Right.
And so when you look at the history of Jewish and Christian interpretation of the story.
of Barak, they tend to praise Deborah.
Right, not Barak.
And Jail, not Barak.
And when you look at the history of Jewish and Christian interpretation of the story of
Jeff the they tend to praise his daughter who he sacrificed.
Yeah, not him.
And see his daughter who obediently went to her death as a type of Christ, right, as sort
of a martyr figure right depending on who.
But you'll hate Jewish.
interpretation, right? So it's entirely likely that if St. Paul, for example, had talked
about parake, he probably would have done the same thing. Yeah. And the same with Jeff
though, right? Because one of the things you find when you compare how St. Paul reads
the scripture to second-table Jewish and early rabbinic interpretations of scripture, they
line up pretty well. Yeah, weirdly enough. You could find where he's getting this stuff,
Right. So he's really not.
going out on a limb on any of these things, right? This is he's interpreting the scriptures correctly,
right? As we should expect from St. Paul. So we can't jump from a question. So the first person at the end
of the second century, who talks about Samson in any kind of detail is St. Paul in his of Rome.
Okay, and...
Saint Apollo, um, and we'll explain what he means, but to put a fine point on it says
that Samson is the forerunner of the anti-Christ. Well, there you go. Not really a great title.
Yeah, not when you want. Uh, so the place where Saint Apollo discusses this is he's,
he's dealing with the tribe of Dan in general, because Saint Apollo argues
list of the 12 tribes.
That he and
This is a prophetic and pointing to the fact that the Antichrist will come from the tribe of Dan.
And so in that context, he goes back to Genesis 49 and the prophecy that we read in the Testament of Jacob about Dan.
That Dan will judge Israel and describing him, right, as the serpent, as the Viper, right.
and says this is a prophecy, he parallels it with the prophecy given to Judah.
The prophecy of Judah is about the, given to Judah is about the Messiah.
The prophecy given about Dan is about the Antichrist, right? The anti Messiah, right?
And so he says in that context, some people say that there's a bit about Dan judging Israel,
right? That part. And then the subsequent part about the Viper and the Snake,
that that's time out right there. Yeah.
They interpret that about Dan as referring to
Hamson, okay? So Saint Hepologus, it does not enter into his head that anyone would have a positive
perception of Samson. Right, right. So he says some people say that Samson, he says he disagrees,
right? He says that's ultimately a prophecy of the Antichrist, but he says
Samson partially fulfills it because Samson is the forerunner of the Antichrist.
Yeah so he's not the
Antichrist. But if you're wondering what the Antichrist looks like, it looks like this guy.
Right. And he makes this comparison that use of the term forerunner is also deliberate,
because he's making a contrast between St. John the Forerunner, St. John the Baptist and Samson.
So as we're going to see in the second half, we're going to talk about
Nazarethites and the New Testament and probably the most prominent. One of those is St. John the Forerunner.
So he makes this comparison between Samson and John the FourRunner,
St. John the FourRunner is the FourRunner of Christ.
He's saying Samson is the FourRunner of Antichrist.
Right?
These two Nazarets, one who keeps all his vows,
one who breaks all his vows.
Right?
So that's St. Apolognes.
I'll say, what else is there Uncle Father Stephen?
Yeah.
So next we can turn to St. Ephraim the Serial.
who at one point in his hymns on paradise is describing the contents of hell. And in one of the
verses describing the contents of hell, he lists the dead bodies of the Nephilim, Goliath,
Samson and Og.
Yeah, also not a very sanctified.
Yeah.
That's where St. Ephraim categorizes him.
So in the past, when I've talked about Samson,
people have gotten mad.
Right.
There are a couple of things they've tried to counter all of this with.
Now you think, already we've got everything scriptures.
We've got everything scriptures.
says, we've got say in
Hipponis, we've got say
never from the Syrian, right?
Not a lot of other church
fathers even talk about Samson.
Right. The only one who really
goes through his life in
detail in terms of preaching
that we still have is St.
Ambrose and St.
Ambrose, it's all a cautionary
tale. It's all, hey, don't
go running after women, young
men, right? Like don't do
what Samson did, right?
Um.
So, you'd think that would represent you being able to say, oh yeah, tradition says
Samson, not a great guy, but some people love that Sunday school Samson experience.
So and are willing to try and fight for it with anything they have.
So the best anybody's done so far, you know, at me, whatever.
is so there's there's this quote from St. John Chrysostom where he's talking about Hebrews.
He's talking about the Everson Hebrews where Samson's name is mentioned. And what he says is,
basically, some people have faulted Paul for including people like Jeff and Samson on this list.
So again, right off the bat, right off the bat, before we...
go any further, right? Say,
Jocross Awesome here acknowledging that the end of the fourth beginning of the fifth century,
that pretty much everybody thinks Samson and Jeff, the for that matter are shady characters
who should not be held up as role models. Yeah. Right. Everyone thinks that. So how does
St. John Chris Awesome defend St. Paul mentioning here him here in this verse of Hebrews? He says,
Listen.
Don't talk to me about their lives.
He literally, he's literally saying,
St. Paul is not holding up their lives for emulation.
St. Paul is not saying you should be like Samson,
right? He says all if he'd kept talking about it,
is use Samson in some way as an example of faith
or something having to do with his story
and we don't know what.
Yeah.
Yeah, the other example that people...
give is that on the Sunday of the four fathers, which is two Sundays before Christmas, there
are two hymns that show up in Mattins, which basically take that list from Hebrews, although
sometimes I'll add some other names to it.
And in front of that list, you see the phrase, let us laud, right?
Let us praise.
and her button.
nothing in particular is said about them. It's just let us
lot, right? So, uh, and I mean, I, I did a pretty thorough
look, like when is, when is Samson actually mentioned in church
hands, right? And this is it. This is literally it, the Sunday
of the four fathers, which is kind of like, so the Sunday the
four fathers and the Sunday the genealogy, but especially the
four fathers, it's just talking about lots and lots of people
from the old testament. If you actually read through the
the long list.
It's lots along lots a lot a long list of names
So you've got these two hymns to say let us laud right
So I mean, let's let's take that and let's would a very long synch sodium so
Synch sodium is is a list of the scenes that are celebrated on that day
You know on this day we commemorate sins so and so on this way of commemorate so so I have you read the whole
Synch sodium it takes it will take a while
most of them it may be a dozen or so names
And this one that goes on for...
pages. And you know, the manans big, big pages. This is a big, big book, like a physically
very large book. And Samson is not in that list. He's not like almost everybody else, but
not Samson and not Jeff, though, by the way, he's not there either. I looked it up. And
even then, you know, what it says is let on this day, we commemorate, which doesn't necessarily
mean that we recognize this person as a whole.
person, but in any event he's not even listed in that way. There's no on this day we commemorate
Samson. And in fact he's not on any of the Sinekzadiyah for the whole year, right? Which that's
the big, that's basically the big list of saints. Now you could say, well, Father Andrew,
maybe he didn't make it into a Sinekzadiyah, and you know, not all the saints do. Okay, okay,
well, what are some other things that we see that would indicate someone's a saint,
and that the church actually...
treats them as a saint, right? Well, there might be icons. There is no Saint-Samson icon. There
are religious paintings of Sampson for sure, but there are no Orthodox icons of Sampson. Oh,
what about is our church's name after him? You know, Saint-Samson Orthodox Church. Once again,
no church is named after him. Is he the patron saint of something or someone or some place or
No.
He-
is not the patron scene of anything.
And when is his feast day?
He does not have a feast day.
So like all the things that you would look for
to indicate, you know, yeah, or, you know,
what about his high geography?
When is, what is his high geography?
Where's his saint's life?
What we got is what's in the book of Judges
and it sure doesn't look good, you know,
that's, that's, so like literally none of the markers
of someone being a saint, being treated as a saint
by the church, like none of them are there.
I searched this pretty thoroughly because I was like, okay, I want to make sure I really,
I really have this down.
So yeah, I mean, don't you don't have to trust me though people.
Go have a look for yourself.
Look at all those sources I just mentioned.
And so this is not even a case of like, you know, some folks, especially folks who come
into the Orthodox Church from a Protestant background, especially from certain types
of evangelical Protestant backgrounds.
of a tendency to
start proof texting, saints and things, right? And liturgics, the way maybe they used to proof text
the Bible. And to be fair, I had an old professor who used to say there's nothing wrong with proof
texts as long as the text actually proves what you're claiming it does, which is rarely the case.
But this is a case where it's not even when you delve into the Orthodox tradition.
to try to understand some issue,
which is how we as Orthodox Christians
should approach issues, right?
You delve deeper into the tradition.
You don't just start theorizing
and constructing something for yourself.
There are some issues that get really complex
because there are some places where it seems like,
for example, different church fathers seem at least
to be saying opposite things
or at least things that don't fit together.
And sometimes it's not just there's like two camps.
sometimes it's a
like there's four or five different views,
right, expressed in different places, right?
You have places where a single church father
seems to contradict themselves sometimes, right?
And that creates this thorny issue
where you have to figure out how to try to reconcile this
and understand what the tradition is really saying,
right, and really teaching.
This is not one of those issues, right?
This is on one side you have the scriptures,
the fathers, right?
like, like, and then on the other side of a matins him at best, like even if we just completely
read that those couple of him are saying, he's a holy man. Yeah, at best, right? But they don't even
say what's good about it. And in that case, right? In that case, taking the approach that, well,
We have to find another way to read the Bible.
Against the grain, another way to read all the
Church fathers who talk about him against the grain.
Another way, right, all the way across the board,
we have to figure out how to reinterpret all that
so that it fits with this one line in a matins him
or maybe,
go out on a limb here, maybe.
We need to reconsider how we interpret
that one line of the matins him to make it fit
with everything else.
That's crazy.
Yes, call me crazy.
Call me crazy.
But right and the reason I'm doing this is not just that I like ruining Sunday
school right although you kind of do I kind of do I'm not saying I don't but that's
not really why we're doing this tonight right because I've talked about Sam's
before the first time we've had an extended discussion of Sam's and on Lord of
Spirits the reason we're doing it tonight is as we're gonna see as we get into
the second and third.
have. If you don't understand what's happening with the interpretation of the story of
Samson, you're not going to get what's going on in the very early history, like New Testament
and immediately post New Testament history of what becomes Christian monasticism. You're
not going to get it if you don't get Samson. There we hear clinging to the Sunday school
version. There we go. All right. Well, with Samson's body safely and
I hate you so long with the dead Nephilim.
We're going to take our first break and we'll be right back with the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Engine Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners with help from Faith Tree Resources.
Are you anxious to grow in your faith, but struggle to carve out time for spiritual disciplines
like prayer or reading Holy Scripture?
You're not alone.
That's why Faith Tree Resources created the Encounter app.
This completely free app for your iPhone or Android device is designed to make the daily
habit of prayer attainable for everyone, no matter how full your schedule is.
The app also includes daily Scripture readings that allow you to listen to the passages being
read aloud.
So whether you've got a lawn commute to...
work or of your hands full with kids, the encounter app makes it easy to get into a daily rhythm
of prayer and reflection.
Join the thousands of Orthodox Christians around the world who gather daily to pray for the
church as the church.
Download the free encounter app today at faithtree.org.
That's faithtree.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question
All now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody.
It's the second half of the show.
Thank you very much, Voice of Steve.
You know, in the past, we can have.
I've actually seen the face of Steve twice
and I'm gonna see him again tomorrow.
It's pretty crazy.
I sometimes when I see him in person,
which isn't super often,
I ask him to do some of these lines to...
to kind of, I don't know, it just feels very homey, you know, you know, I'm saying father.
I'm guessing it's not. Yeah, okay, there he is.
Yes, yes, yes. Okay, Samson. You know, what not to do?
But are there Nazarets? Yeah, there's Nazarets in the Bible, right? And the New Testament,
and of course they're in the Bible,
and the New Testament as well.
So, yeah, I mean, people not cutting their hair, not drinking the drink, not, not, you know,
closer to the dead bodies.
Not hanging out with dead souls, yeah.
Yeah.
Right.
So I mean, here's the question.
Could a nasorite go to a hot topic?
Should a nasorite go to the hot topic?
We need a ruling.
Does he have to start the vow over if he enters a hot topic?
Are they dead souls?
Yeah, it's an interesting question.
If you're a rabbioliciting to this,
call in and answer that question for us.
Give us a room.
Oh man, that happens.
Yes.
That would be amazing.
So in the New Testament, right,
this isn't something that gets jettisoned.
We've talked before how there's almost nothing actually
from the Old Testament that really
fits that category of being jettisoned.
But things get...
transformed, right? They get fulfilled, they get embodied in ways, this is going
somewhere, they get embodied in ways that transform them. And so the figure who's
going to kind of embody the Nazarite tradition from the Torah in the New
Testament in a transformative way, you know, fulfilling way is St John the
four out of it.
the Baptist who we already mentioned. Right. And we mentioned the contrast between he and Samson
that Saint Apollitus makes. But Saint Apollitus again is not just reaching up and pulling this out
of the air. This isn't a peculiar, let me just say since I realized it in the spirit of self-criticism.
I just reached my hand into the air and made a motion of grabbing something out of the
Are you one of the people that gestures when you're on the phone with somebody?
Yes.
You do that?
Anyway, back to what I was saying.
You point.
Look over, wait.
It's saying to politists.
It does not.
Despite my lonely gesticulations.
Say to politists does not just pull this out of the air.
And it's not just a peculiarity between the prophecy to Judah and the one to Dan.
This is also something he's getting from the New Testament, right?
Because when you read, for example, Luke 1 verses 13 through 17, that part of the story
of the prediction of St John the Four Hunters birth, St. Luke is very clearly drawing some
deliberate parallels with the story of the announcement of Samson's birth in the book
of Judges.
Yeah.
So I'm going to read these verses and people can...
We'll hear it now, given everything we just said about Naz writes in the previous half.
Starting with verse 13, but the angel said to him,
Do not be afraid, Zachariah, for your prayer has been heard,
and your wife Elizabeth will bear you a son,
and you shall call his name John.
And you will have joy and gladness,
and many will rejoice at his birth,
for he will be great before the Lord.
And he must not drink wine or strong drink,
and he will be filled with the Holy Spirit
even from his mother's womb,
and he will turn many of the children of Israel
to the Lord their God,
and he will go before him in the Spirit and power of Elijah.
you
to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children and the disobedient to the wisdom of the just to make ready for the Lord a
people prepared.
I mean, this is like what a judge should have really should have been in every way, you know,
Right. He's setting things up putting things in right order. Right and notice in terms of that fulfillment
We get the verb use there in that he will be filled from the Holy Spirit even from his mother's womb
Yeah, and we find out in the St. Luke's
that he means that very literally, right?
Because he leaps in the womb, right?
When the Theotokos enters with Christ in her womb.
But so the Holy Spirit kind of comes,
it seizes him to do God's will,
but in general he is not.
Compared to the Holy Spirit coming
in a dwelling St John the Forerunner.
Yeah, I mean, there's a line in like,
I mean, there's multiple points.
Yeah, multiple points.
I'm looking at this now
in the Samson story.
where it says that the Spirit of the Lord rushed upon him.
Rushed upon him.
I mean, over and over again, three different times.
Yeah.
So this is God grabbing him and doing what he wants to do.
It's almost like Samson is a puppet.
Like, so Samson is not gonna credit for it.
Yeah.
Right?
He's not even, that rushed upon, right?
He's not even presented as cooperating per se.
Right.
And, of course, an obvious contrast as he mentioned,
is Saint John keeps his vows.
Right?
And it's even commented upon.
Christ comments on it when he's talking about the differ,
they call him a drunkard and a glutton.
Right?
So this isn't just talking about drinking water.
Right.
This is talking about that part of the vow.
Right?
But in terms of that fulfillment.
And in terms of his embodiment of the Nazarite tradition,
and how that tradition gets sort of advanced and transformed in the figure of St. John the Forerunner,
we see him incorporate, and that's already in that prophecy about his birth,
incorporating these elements from the prophet Elijah from St. Elias.
And you can go back to our episode, make straight the paths for our God.
we're talking about sage on the forerunner we get more into that the relationship between
him and the prophet Elijah and say the lius.
But right be sort of physically set apart in that way.
Some of the other elements of asceticism and especially it needs to be noted it will be
developing this a little more.
This idea of chastity.
Yeah.
Right.
your point of contrast between say each other 400 and Samson.
Yeah, so we actually have a couple of people who have called in.
Okay.
Yeah.
So are you with us about Sam's?
I don't know.
We'll find out.
Okay.
So first we've got Mark who is calling from Wisconsin and Mark wants to talk about Samson's
famous murder slash suicide.
So Mark, are you there?
Are you triggered, Mark?
Yeah.
No, I'm not triggered.
Okay.
But I got my gun just in case I am.
You can't shoot people through the phone mark.
Okay, I won't do it. Here's my take on that and then you tell me if I'm way off base or maybe clarify it so
Samson the bad dude that he is asked God to give him strength to pull down the pillars
So then Samson has faith that God will grant it so got him what he wants
therefore he doesn't
compromises free will or free choice, even though it turns out bad for Samsung and
And that's the consequences of man's free will and choice.
Did I get that right or do you need to clarify that better?
I don't know.
Go ahead, Father.
Yeah, go ahead.
I was just going to say, I don't know that faith necessarily enters into it.
Okay.
All right.
In that, what he literally says is, give me my strength back one time so I can get revenge
for my eyes.
Okay.
Okay, so right.
So I interpreted that as Samson had faith that God would grant him his wish even
goal was for evil. Well, I mean, pray did said, you know, I've broken all my
vows right? I haven't I haven't been faithful giving my strength back so that I
can redeem Israel from these Philistines. Okay. And do your will with my last act.
right like he could have said that.
Yep, yep.
But his goal was not to kill the Philistines because that's what God had led him to do or
directed him to do.
It was to get personal revenge for what they did to him.
Right.
And then God granted him that strength to do that.
Because it serves God's purposes, right?
Just like, just like, you know, as we've seen with this concept of the left hand of God,
demons do their will and God permits them to do it because it serves God's purposes.
right? Like even like if I take that and personalize it, sometimes I'll do stupid things because of my free will and
free choice. And God allows that. He doesn't say, no, no, you're not going to do that. I'm not going to let you do that. He goes,
you're going to do it. And hopefully you'll learn from it and repent. Right. And God could bring good out of it. I mean, like the story of Joseph, right? His brothers intent was evil. But God brought good out of it. Right. Okay. And on one last thing,
Thank you.
Father Steven, you were one of the first people I watched on YouTube when I was considering
becoming Orthodox.
And two years ago on August 9th, 2020, I was Christmas.
I was a former Roman Catholic.
I'm Christmas.
So you were kind of the Geet Keeper, so to speak.
So I want to thank you for that.
And I appreciate all that you two guys do for Orthodoxy and everybody.
Well, thank God.
Amen.
You bet.
Thanks for calling, Mark. All right. You two. All right. Well, we've got Georgia and her phone
number at least says she's in Alabama. I don't know. Georgia, are you there? I am here. Can you
hear me? We can hear you. Are you in Alabama? Or are you traveling with us on the phone?
I am in Alabama. It's good that you called in because you were on our mind.
Yeah. Right. Well, we're the sister state of Louisiana. So I had to represent for the south.
So my question has to do with hair.
And what does this, how should we understand
these passages in the Bible which talk about hair?
And they seem to relate somehow to chastity or sexuality.
But there's kind of a lot going on in the Bible with hair,
with women having to cover their heads.
Because of the angels, I have no idea what that means.
you know, and the Nazareas having to wear their hair long.
And then even later we see iconography of Christ, you know, in the early
first century, the Christianity shift from having short hair to having kind of a long
Nazareist style of hair.
So how should we interpret this?
How would ancient people see this?
That's a good question.
That's a lot of things through it.
Yeah.
I remember, I mean, I'm just going to pass on something that I was told in seminary, but
I don't know if it's...
wrong or not. So I'll be interested to hear what Father Stevens says about this. But I remember
one of the conversations I had when I was in seminary class was the idea that hair
kind of marks a border between things. So in the case of a Nazarete vow or in the case of,
as we're going to see with monasticism, but also in the case of baptism, there's moving from one
One way of life into another way of life.
And also, as you mentioned, there's elements of sexuality as well.
And, you know, without getting into that, but I mean, that there's a kind of border there, right?
So at least that's one way that I, and it makes sense to me.
I don't know, Father, what else might there be?
Or, you know, you want to um actually me?
Well, I'm not going to really, I'm actually, I am going to just go for it though.
So fair warning here it comes.
Uh, okay.
So the parental warning or
I think I could do this where we won't need one.
Okay.
It'll depend on how many of what kind of follow-up questions could ask.
So there's really, so there's sort of two layers to this that are both part of your question.
Right, so one layer is related to what we've been talking about tonight and that what
what Father Andrew is pointing to.
So there is a...
with the shaving of the head, sort of, and like I talked about with the foreign woman
who comes into Israel shaving her head, the shaving the head at the beginning and end
of the Nazarete vow as being part of this sort of new beginning, right, beginning again.
Like a trauma haircut, sort of thing.
Right.
Yeah.
I just father Andrew said, you know, this change in way of life.
Right.
I did a trauma haircut once.
I think we've all.
I was a much younger man and my girlfriend had broken up with me.
Oh, you did the Desk Brit cry for hell, Pearcut.
Yeah.
Well, I used to be a long hair hippie type when I was a stage head.
And then it was all gone.
Not all of it, but you know, the majority of it.
Yeah.
I mean, now I couldn't even grow it if I wanted to.
But.
Yes.
Well, you could, I think you could pull off the skull it, right?
the Hulk Hogan Herc.
So, yeah, and then the element of not cutting it, right, is at all, right?
And this is something that's carried through in monasticism, right?
Like after the torture, right?
Like male monastics don't cut their hair and their beards.
That has an L
element of sort of vanity to it and concern with that sort of thing, right, that you're
not your focus and your concern, your dedication is not to sort of the presentation of your
personal appearance. When you're talking about what St. Paul says in first Corinthians,
right, there's another layer that's coming in here because St. Paul is talking to the
people of Corinth who are former pagans.
And probably first and second Corinthians out of St. Paul's writings that are included
in the New Testament are the ones that are most clearly aimed at former pagans.
That's as opposed to Jewish Christians and Christians who were Godfairers, who were Gentiles
associated with the synagogue.
Just straight out these people were worshiping pagan gods, now they're Christians.
That's why there's this...
unique set of problems in first and second Corinthians. And then ongoing, say,
Clement has to write to Corinth, right? Because, you know,
they have issues, right? Your Godfirs that your Jewish Christians are going to be tempted to go
eat meat off or offer to idols or participate in a feast at an idol's temple, right? They already
know that's bad, right? And so when he's addressing women's hair in particular there,
He's and talks about
men's hair like long hair being ashamed to a man.
And the people say, well, wait, what about,
say, to the forerunner, what about monastics,
what about data?
Right.
So he's speaking now to what we would call Greco.
So if you read and not a lot of people do,
but if you go and read the Hippocratic Corpus,
which is the collection, it's named after Hippocrates,
it's not all written by Hippocrates.
It's the collection of...
Greek medical texts that we still have essentially,
ancient Greek medical texts.
The Hippocratic oath is same hypocrite.
It talks about the way in Greek culture,
the Roman period they believed hair worked.
And they believed that hair attracted
hair
Attracted and
held male seed that entered the body.
Therefore, long hair on anyone, right, displayed long hair on anyone, culturally
represented openness to physical relationships, not necessarily within the
context of a marriage and fertility. And so if a man wore his hair long in that
culture, it was a sign that they were open to same sex fornication. And if a woman
openly war-long hair.
that was a sign that she was available to men.
And so St. Paul is saying to these two are coming out of that culture,
that kind of sexual display does not belong on a man ever,
and does not belong on a woman in the context of the church community.
Right.
So the kind of signal that it's sending right and so people who say it's modesty that's not wrong
But I mean it's sort of more than that in the original setting. Yeah modesty within a specific
Kind of mental neck type of thing right and
Dropping that line about because of the angels is
Saint Paul
Making a reference to the fact that when we're gathered together in the church community right that we're joining the worship in heaven
the end.
are there, right? And he's dropping a not very subtle reference to like the book of
Enic traditions about women and angels. Okay. Not to be taken literally like you think
if a woman doesn't wear a head covering that's going to happen again and she's going to have
giant babies, right? That's not like literally, right? But he's alluding to that. He's alluding
to that to make the point that...
within the Israelite Jewish Christian tradition, right?
As it goes through those phases, through that whole tradition,
up to and including the Christian tradition,
that are two completely unrelated things
that need to be kept away from each other,
which we take for granted,
but if you were living in 1st century Corinth,
So, I think I've done that in a way that...
No one heard anything they shouldn't, but hopefully that answered your question nonetheless.
Probably not.
Yes, it did.
All right.
I really regret asking it now, but I understand.
Oh, man.
I think you're the first person ever to say that to us, but TMI.
TMI.
There's a lot more going on there than you mentioned.
Yeah, did not expect that one.
All right.
I see it only took three.
years to have. Oh yeah. Yeah. Well, you know, it's not that I ever have cared about self-protection
and not getting canceled. But in those early days, but also, I mean, to you and the same
one they should face. That's so nice of you. I didn't want to cause trouble for you folks,
necessarily. Now you're untouchable. No, no, no, I don't get in trouble. I stay in trouble. I just
You just want to drag-
I go home with other people down with it, but it just so happens at this episode is about
hair among other things. So I get it's topical. It's top. If you call with a topical question,
everybody, we will, we will take it. Or occasionally, we may also say, well, we're actually about
to get to that. Yeah. So yeah, right. We haven't gotten the angry Samsonites though. I know, I guess,
I don't know. They maybe they just don't listen to the show. I don't know. Yeah. Or they're
They're just so frothing with rage they can't even duck.
Yeah, just exactly.
Yeah, so say John the Forerunner, live it in the wilderness.
Yes.
Well, yeah, no, so we were talking about him.
So yeah, it's a tragedy.
Say John the Forerunner, he adds these elements from the prophet Elijah sort of through his embodiment
of the Nazarite tradition that's going to become important going further.
But he's not the only place, even though he's probably the only one, the average
first.
and might know off the top of their head.
So one of these is a question.
In that, and this is St. James the Joss.
This is St. James the brother of the Lord.
Yes, his step brother, the son of Joseph.
Yes, St. James the Adelphos,
the Acabos the Adelphos for all our Greek list.
So there is nothing
in the New Testament scriptures.
that really tells us that St. James was in Azerite.
That's why this is a question.
But within, and some of these folks aren't technically church fathers,
so it is ecclesiastical history,
Hadesipus, so we're getting the second hand to boot.
Hadesipus says that St. James was in Azerite.
And then he was a life.
long Nazarete. Now that also though isn't totally clear because much like
monasticism, lifelong Nazarete does not necessarily mean that his parents made
him one. Right. You could become a lifelong Nazarete at any age. So we saw
Samson and St John the Four Runner worse from birth, right? Their birth is
announced. But which is one of the things that
them together, but your average lifelong Nazarite would be like someone who we would say was a
lifelong monk. That doesn't mean like after they were born they are carried to a monastery, right?
That usually means when they came of age as a young person, they joined, spent the rest of their
life as a monastic, right? And so all that is to say, if St. James is one, so we have these two
places that mention it. We don't have anything that says he wasn't one.
We just only have a couple of mentions on it, right? So it's hard to conclude based on that. Oh, yeah, for sure, right?
Now that does fit with
Josephus has a fairly extended description of St. James
Talking about his piety
The way he was always in the temple the camel needs thing that he was referred to as camel needs because
He had knees like a camel from kneeling in the temple. Yeah
Yeah, they're certain so big.
Yeah.
Huge calluses.
Yeah. That's certainly compatible with the idea that he was a Nazarite, but he had dedicated
himself to the Lord in this way. But it's also possible to dedicate your life to the service
of the Lord without necessarily having it be in the context of a Nazarite vow. We just don't know.
There's these comments about it. Yeah. We know that St. Paul took a temporary Nazarite vow himself.
Yeah, yeah, I mean X-
1818 it says after this Paul stayed many days longer and then took leave of the brothers and set sail for Syria and with him
Priscilla and Aquila at Kenkriye he had cut his hair for he was under a vow
That's pretty clearly a reference to an azuretik vow. Yeah, but now the more controversial one
Now we come to Acts 21
Yes
Yes, Acts 21 verses 17 through 26
Welcome to Controvers.
episode of Lord of Spirits. This one is so controversial based on what I'm going to say. This
isn't going to ruin Sunday school. No. This is controversial because people avoid X21.
You may not even realize that people avoid X21 but people avoid X21.
because for a lot of folks with a lot of their
different theological structures and ideas.
And commit as it were.
Yes, Acts 21 is where they go to die.
Right.
All right.
Acts 21 wrecks a lot of theories about the relationship
between Judaism and Christianity,
about the relationship between sacrifices
of the Eucharist.
Yeah.
So let's just dive in.
Yeah, let's just add so this is when this is just to sort of give the back right? This is when
we're near the end of the book of the Acts of the Apostles. St Paul has come back to
Jerusalem. He's facing a lot of opposition. This is all going to culminate in his arrest.
Okay, but as we pick up, he's just arriving back in Jerusalem, right?
And that's that's where
this quote begins.
Okay.
Acts 21, starting with verse 17,
When we had come to Jerusalem, the brothers received us gladly.
On the following day, Paul went in with us to James, and all the elders were present.
After greeting them, he related one by one the things that God had done among the Gentiles
through his ministry.
And when they heard it, they glorified God.
And they said to him, you see, brother, how many thousands there are among the Jews of
those who have believed?
They are all zealous for the law and they are...
been told about you that you teach all the Jews who are among the Gentiles to forsake Moses,
telling them not to circumcise their children or walk according to our customs. What then is to
be done? It was certainly here that you have come. Do therefore what we tell you. We have four
men who are under a vow. Take these men and purify yourself along with them and pay their expenses
so that they may shave their heads. Thus all will know that there is nothing in what they have
been told about you but that you...
yourself also live in observance of the law. But as for the Gentiles who have believed,
we have ascended a letter with our judgment that they should abstain from what has been sacrificed
to idols and from blood and from what has been strangled and from sexual immorality.
And Paul took the men, and the next day he purified himself along with them,
and went into the temple, giving notice when the days of purification will be fulfilled,
and the offering presented for each one of them. So clearly there's these four groups,
these four guys that are under an azuretic bow.
They have to get their haircut, they have to offer the sacrifices and Paul is paying for all of that.
And their Christians.
And their offerings sacrifices at the temple as
is including a sin offering.
Yeah.
At the end of their vows.
And say Paul totally cool with it.
Yeah, he goes along with the whole thing.
consuring it to show that he has not rejected the law of Moses.
Right. Yeah. And notice what it says here. But as for those Gentiles who have believed,
just those four things. Yeah, we sent a letter. And you know, as opposed to St. James, St. Paul,
and these four guys who are Jewish Christians. Yeah. Yeah.
Yes. So, a lot of people's ideas about through between Judaism and Christianity, among other things,
is.
like there's this idea that, you know, with Christ's death on the cross,
and it's rising from the dead, that the entire system of sacrifices and all of that stuff is over.
And so of course, Christians would never do that because Jesus has been sacrificed now
and you don't need any of that stuff anymore.
And yet here they are, not just fulfilling Nazaritic vows, but actually offering sacrifices at the temple,
which includes animals.
animals.
Thank you.
It was a sin offering.
Yeah.
sin offering in particular. Yes. Right. So now that we've established the problematic. So this is
you know this hopefully this episode will be helpful in terms of method. Right? Because
we just read this scripture. This is the Bible. Right. This is the Holy Scriptures.
They're telling us this thing.
from the perspective of a lot of our preconceived notions, this seems wrong. Right? So, what do you do? Well,
you have to be ready to break your preconceived notions and go with what the scriptures tell us. Right?
the reality is, we have this period of time from 80, 30 to 80, 70, 40 years, right?
40 years.
One generation of...
where Christ has died and risen again and the veil has been torn, but the temple is still there.
And this passage we just heard is just one example of the fact that the Scriptures present that the Christians,
the Jewish Christians still made full use of it for that 40 years.
years. Um, as I said, this is just one place, right?
Saint Louis.
gospel ends before Acts picks up the end of St. Luke's gospel, which we're after the resurrection,
being in the temple worshiping God day and night, the temple of Jerusalem.
So they're making full use of it as we see here. They're making offerings.
So yeah, there are many such cases.
Right. And we all...
We also have to fit this together with, like we talked about, not that long ago in this
series, an episode on the Eucharist, the understanding of the Eucharist as a sacrifice,
instituted by Christ, the sacrifice of Christ with its own priesthood, with its own priesthood.
And so there's this new sacrifice in this new priesthood.
Right. And we tend to jump the gun a little. Right. So if if you're on the page, right,
which some of our Protestant friends are not, but if you're on the page that the Eucharist
is a sacrifice. And without going into it all here, I don't think you can escape that.
There's a journal article online of mine. You can find where I argue from first Corinthians
that St. Paul explicitly says it's a sacrifice.
There's just not a way around it exigenically.
So, if you're on the page that the Eucharist is a sacrifice, right?
We tend to jump to, okay, well the Eucharist just replaces all of those temple sacrifices.
So when we see, like this, with St. Paul offering sacrifices, and particularly St.
offerings in the temple, it's brain breaking, right? Like, no, they
Paul don't do it right?
There was already within the Torah, right?
There's already a means of distinguishing different levels and different types of sacrifice.
So for example, one that's kind of clear is the distinction between the sort of daily
sin offerings that are offered and the day of atonement.
So one of the questions when you're doing research and trying to understand what's going
of the day of atonement is wise.
the day of atonement even necessary once a year. If you have these daily sin offerings,
isn't sin being taken care of in the context of these daily sin offerings? Why do you need
this other annual thing? Right? So there's this distinction made because there's seen to
be doing different things. We talked about this when we talked about the day of atonement
at the end of our sacrifice. Right? The day of atonement is doing a different thing than
the sin offerings.
And so these sacrifices aren't like competing with each other.
Yeah.
But doing different things.
Yeah, I mean, in context, they're used to a life with all these different kinds of sacrifices.
Right.
You know, that this idea, this, you know, frankly, that some Protestants have that, you know, all of that is now ended because of Jesus' sacrifice.
That's anachronistic if you're kind of in the moment because no one was thinking about.
or probably no one, I mean, we don't know what they're thinking, but we have no evidence
than anyone thought of the sacrificial system as being all one ball of something that
then would be replaced by one other thing.
Right.
And if you took the Tartus back and told one of the Jewish Christians in and around Jerusalem
during this 40 years that they had joined a new religion they tell you you are crazy.
Yeah.
From their perspective, they haven't joined a new religion.
Right.
They're still Jewish.
They just believe Jesus is the Messiah and that he has instituted the Eucharist.
Right.
They're celebrating the Eucharist on the Lord's Day.
You have the Sabbath and then you have the Lord's Day.
Right.
And they're celebrating the Eucharist on the Lord's Day.
And when you read the New Testament closely,
Christ's sacrifice is seen specifically and especially to be fulfilling the Passover and
the Day of Atonement.
And we've talked about this a bunch, right?
We've talked about the Passover connections are obvious, or PASCA, it's Passover.
We still celebrate as Christians, the Christian Passover, which is the celebration of the resurrection
of Christ, right?
So.
Passover, and then also the Day of Atonement.
And in that phrase, the Lamb of God who takes away the sin
of the world, Passover and the Day of Atonement
are drawn together.
Yeah, yeah.
Right, the go to takes away sin and the Passover Lamb
are pulled together.
That's primarily what, in the view of the New Testament,
which is coming out of this generation of Jewish Christians,
That's the primary fulfillment.
So it is natural for them.
Now, when the time comes to celebrate Passover, they're celebrating the Christian Passover.
And the Eucharist is a participation in Christ's sake.
But that it's serving a different function.
Then, for example, the sacrifice is offered at the end of a Nazarete vow.
What happens is, then, the temple gets destroyed.
Yep, in the year 70.
And when the temple gets destroyed,
all of the various Judaism's that exist in the second temple period
have to try to cope, right?
And some of them do extremely poorly.
So if you're a Sadducee and you're whole power-based,
well, now that the temple's gone, you're done.
So more Sadducees.
Yep, right.
Yep.
The Pharisees did much better.
Right? Because the Pharisees were already ambivalent toward the temple.
Yeah, their whole thing is synagogue focus. Right.
They were focused on the worship of the synagogue. Right.
Even during the through the second temple period, they were more focused on the synagogue
and on the keeping of the Torah, not on the temple.
And so they were able to compensate when the temple went away.
They tended to, and this is what you see in later rabbinic Judaism.
They saw certain periods and types of prayer and fasting as
Performing the function that had previously been performed by the animal sacrifices in the temple
Right and so
even
Jewish people in the contemporary period
Who are more in that line of thought than extends back to the Pharisees
Don't particularly want the temple back
They still have that
of ambivalent attitude. Right, it's another category of Zionism that wants the temple back desperately.
But so that becomes rabbinic Judaism. The other major Judaism that survives the
destruction of the temple is Christianity. And Christianity still has a sacrifice and a priesthood,
still has the Eucharist and the Eucharistic priesthood.
when the temple is destroyed.
And so what happens is Christians see the Eucharist as the sacrifice instituted by Christ as fulfilling
the purpose of all of the sacrifices.
This is where then, this is why you start to see the move in this very early period
period from having the Eucharist on the Lord's Day every week to having the
Eucharist every day. Because the Eucharist is now seen to also be fulfilling the function
of those daily sacrifices that had been offered in the temple. For Jewish and then also for Gentile
Christians as it shifts and as it spreads. So this may be the other controversial part.
Right.
Uh, the episode.
Uh.
And basically, but we have to, we can't just hand wave,
Acts 21.
No, it's part of our scriptures.
It's read in our electionary cycle, our electionary
in the Orthodox Church is not skip it.
It's not embarrassed of it, right?
This has to fit into our understanding, right?
It's scripture.
Also, just for the record, by way of deflecting
something I know will show up in my email box.
of the next couple of days. I have no memory of this, but I may have said something different
about Acts 21 on the whole Council of God some years ago when I went through Acts. If so,
I was wrong then. What? I may still be wrong now, but I was definitely wrong then. Oh, there you go.
So save yourself that email. I'm not going to try to defend or reconcile whatever it was I said.
Unless I said the same.
thing. Then I'm remarkably consistent. Who knows? Then you're still going with that. Yeah.
Yeah. So, okay. So are there any kind of Nazarites, Nazarites, Nazaritic? See, I'm trying to say
both at the same time, practices. Right. We see quite the fact that we now don't have a
temple to offer those sacrifices from X-21 at the end of the vow. We do find these tantalizing
references in
Syria, so from early Christianity in Syria that refer to Christian Nazarites.
And this seems to be part and parcel of the very early history of monasticism in Syria,
is that it began with sort of Christian Nazarites.
But already here, we see the incorporation of some of the
elements of the life of St. John the forerunner, life in the wilderness, other
ascetic disciplines beyond just the Nazarite rules, that kind of thing.
Yeah, it's a higher form because it's got more, there's more to it than just the
three original vows. Right, right. And there is still this emphasis on the
cutting of the hair. Some of these sources where you could read about this are in
and St. Ed from the Syrian and Afrahat who may remain known.
Well, I won't get into that.
Um, on for hot in particular though, uh,
uses Samson as a bad example
in talking to these Christian
Nazarites.
Yeah, don't be like that.
He says, uh, he did well
in making his vows, but then he fell from his vows
through fornication or through licentiousness.
Sorry, licentiousness.
So what you see here is that it's sort of through Samson as bad example, monastic over
against H. John the Forerunner as good example, that the element of chastity of virginity comes
into the picture of these vowed or sanctified individuals.
Right. That's that's expressly right here is where
comes in, right, that even though Samson didn't take any kind of vow of chastity, right,
that it was through his licentiousness that he ended up breaking all of his other vows.
And therefore, when we make this comparison to St John the Four Runner, St John the Four
Runner's chastity and virginity is seen as part and parcel of him having capped all of
the other vows.
Yeah, it's it.
Right. Yeah. Right. And so this then becomes this is sort of the prehistory, right, of Christian
monasticism here in these Syriac sources, right, bubbling up. All right. Well, that's
the end of the second half. We still have a third half to go. So we will be right back
in just a moment with more Lord of Spirits. Father Andrew Stephen, David and Father
Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your call.
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
This is Father Stephen Freeman.
I'm happy to announce ancient faiths publication
of my latest book,
face to face knowing God beyond our shame.
Some modern therapists have described shame as the master emotion.
One that colors and shapes our world in ways that we hardly imagine.
The Christian tradition is no stranger to this and has a rich understanding of the ways this part of our inner life shapes our experience of the world.
This book offers something of a roadmap to that inner life.
What is shame?
Is it always bad?
Does it have any useful?
for us. Join me in an exploration of knowing God beyond our shame, finding the true God
whom the scriptures tell us did not turn his face from the spitting and the shame. Face
to face is now available at store.AncientFaith.com. That's store.AncientFaith.com.
3, 7, 2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855.
A-F radio.
All right welcome back is the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'd like to verify something before we go any further.
Oh yeah go for it.
Father Stephen Freeman and I are not the same person.
It's true.
I think we did got contacted by someone recently that
that can refer to Father Stephen Freeman on Lord of Spirits.
Yes.
Yeah right.
Yeah, maybe we just...
saw it somewhere. I'm assuming you're confusing the two actual father Stevens's or father's
Stephen. They may have confused you and him, right? They may think you're also father's
Stephen. Who knows how deep the confusion goes. But father's Stephen Freeman are not the
same person. A year ago, we were in the same place at the same time seen together. And
This was not like when Alfred dressed-
up his Batman. We both had our respective facial hair and were our respective sizes. Yeah.
Yeah. He and you are not the same size. Not. Yeah. And we are. So they're for very clearly
not the same person. Right. And so don't don't send hate mail aimed at me to him. He's
in that to me. He goes to yes. He doesn't deserve it. I find it entertaining. I forward
Bye- for-
good ones to Father Steve. Yeah, if you want to send hate mail directed at Father
Steve and Freeman to me, I'll read it and laugh at it, but that probably won't give you
the kind of visceral thrill you're looking for in sending the hate mail in the first place.
For when it's worth. Thank you for that clarification. Yes, it's important once in a while.
Amen. Amen. So, all right, well, we've been talking about
that, uh, nasorites.
and making our way to see each other for one or another and so forth.
So let's talk about now Christian monasticism and how it blossomed out of all of that.
This fits in with the generic Lord of Spirits script where you get to the thing in the third half.
Exactly.
And sometimes just spend 30 seconds mentioning it.
So it's all right, it's been happening here.
There's actually not a lot to, I mean, I looked this up, there's actually not a lot to
the actual service of making someone a monk or not.
It's really a brief little like a couple of prayers, honestly.
It's not an elaborate ritual that we can walk you through.
But it is a mystery of the church, it is a sacrament.
Indeed.
That's why we've been having this brawm.
So it's important, I think.
in addressing now Christian monasticism and our understanding of it and what it is and how it works actually to dip back
ever so briefly into the Old Testament one more time and
this is to
Look at Amos chapter two verses 11 and 12
Amos gets overlooked
a lot
Alright, you all testament Joel
Right, you get the pentacost stuff, right?
The Holy Spirit being poured out on all flesh.
Right?
Jose gets told to go and marry a prostitute.
That's kind of exciting and interesting.
Amos from Ticoa, he gets left out a lot.
Off it's in Nazareids.
And so a couple things that pairing shows you.
First of all, from this text, right?
God calls and raises up.
now
or monastics in our modern terms. These are people who God calls and raises up and calls them
to this particular way of life, to be people set apart in the same way that he calls
and sets a profits, to serve this function for him in relation to the larger community.
Right, of followers of God.
That's number one.
a specific calling from God for the purpose of the body. And in particular, this connection
between Nazareth and Prophet is also one of roll, that that purpose that they serve in
in terms of the body is not completely dissimilar.
Yeah.
Right.
So...
monastic tonture. Here it is. Here's this sacrament. Right. This is the material act. Right. So we've seen all the sacraments.
God working through material things, whether it's water and baptism, oil, chrysum,
uh, uh, male and female human organism in the case of marriage. Right.
And here it's hair.
that hair being physically cut.
Yeah, and for maybe some of our non-orthodox listeners and we're happy to have you.
If you don't know what monastic cancer is, basically there's a couple of prayers that are
said by the abbot of the monastery and then he takes scissors and he cuts bits of the
the hair of the person becoming a monk or a nun in a crosswise form, it says.
So usually that means a little bit at the front, a little bit at the back, and then a little bit on each of the two sides.
And then that hair typically is then put into a sensor, you know, burned typically.
And that's kind of the key moment.
You know, they'll often, depending on the tradition they may put particular, they will definitely put a NASA clothing on them, but it kind of depends on
which tradition they're in as to which clothing that gets put on them.
but at what point?
Yeah, they're life. Yeah, there might be, yeah, there might be sort of steages of this depending on the the monastic tradition
And they'll often give them a hand cross and they'll be usually a candle there
So they're holding a candle which is similar in some ways to when someone is baptized
And that kind of a fellow meant with the hair cutting. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's that's and there's a new name too
Actually, they're given a new name. Yeah
Which they don't know beforehand by the way the Abbott or or Abbott's
just picks that name.
Um, um, add some to any, if there are any habits or abs is listening to this show, sham
gar.
Yeah.
Come on, guys or ladies, excuse me, uh, mothers, fathers.
I was going to say, I don't know guys and ladies.
Why just start to say it's come on guys and I'm like, no, no, no, no, such an arrogant.
I know.
So so informal.
Yeah, and yes, so the person.
doesn't know beforehand what the name they're going to get is it's their first active obedience.
This is your new name. It could be, you know, Epaphroditus or whatever. Shamgar.
Yeah. And all of that is aimed just like, right, the beginning of the Nazarete.
Well, you're making this new beginning, new person, right, new start.
So going forward from sort of where we left off, right, into the history of Christian monasticism,
You
There's some important figures, some important saints,
important places related to monasticism, right?
Where again, these things that are developing
in this Nazarectric verse to go out into the desert,
specifically the Egyptian desert.
So we're talking with San Anthony,
we're talking around circa AD 270.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and...
So third century AD, most of what we know about him, there are other lives of St. Anthony,
but sort of the core text is St. Athanasius of Alexandria's life of St. Anthony.
And St. Anthony famously sold all of his possessions, went out to the desert at first.
sort of apprenticed with a particular hermit.
who was already kind of practicing.
So this is, let's be clear.
St. Anthony the Great, not the first monastic.
Not the first Christian monastic.
Yeah, I mean, there's St. Paul of Thebes is out there first, right?
Yeah.
Even if we're just talking about the Egyptian desert.
Yeah, just a different desert, right or right?
Yeah.
And in fact, St. Anthony had a sister
when St. Anthony inherited all of his parents' possessions
gave them away.
He had his sister go and live with the community of female virgins. Well, what's what's that?
You're right. Yeah. It's a female monastic community that already existed, right?
But we're famously he he uses the
skull of the former resident as a pillow
And in that tomb he suffered a series of demonic both Orthodox iconography and
and very imaginative Western...
art depicting the temptation of St. Anthony in the cave tomb.
And ultimately then went to live a life of solitude as a hermit himself on top of a particular
mountain.
Despite his original intent to live in solitude on the top of that mountain, people were
attracted to him in his way of life and began to also go and live
the mountain and whenever they could encounter it, they prevailed upon him to become sort of the
abbots, the father, the leader of their monastic community. Eventually around the year 305 he
relented and did that. Probably his most famous disciple is St. Macarius the Great
and you can read, there's literature from him, he's one of the greatest of the Desert Fathers.
There's there's
there's a kind of funny episode where St. Constantine sent him a letter, uh, sort of to ask him for
guides and wisdom, but, but did it in the way that a Roman emperor sends a letter to a common person?
St. Anthony was completely out of breast with,
getting a letter from the Roman emperor and, uh, sent him a letter back basically telling him he
he should stop spending all his time.
worrying about worldly affairs, that Roman Emperor should spend less time worrying about earthly affairs,
which is advised that technically after his baptism, St. Constantine eventually took.
But yeah, that was his reply. He also at one point sort of emerged in Alexandria out of the desert to
to condemn areas.
But so in the life of saying that again, this is kind of a theme, I guess, of the episode
is that so you don't what you don't find with menacism, there's Nazarete tradition developing
into the the menacic tradition.
You don't find a lot of people sitting around theorizing about it.
Yeah, they're just doing it.
Right.
three to six about you find people go.
it embodying it. Right. Going out and living a certain life, living a certain way of life,
and that then attracts other people to that way of life. Right. As a way of pursuing
sort of the life that they're embodying. And so the life of St. Anthony, the life he can
completely lives becomes the paradigm for the Egyptian desert monastic for the desert father
of Egypt.
You know, it's interesting to think about,
and we're going to...
to talk about Manothos in just a second, but it's interesting to think about, you know,
Athos got to the point in the modern era where I think there were fewer than a thousand
monks there and a place where there once had been 40,000, right?
Some is really, it really dwindled over centuries.
And what's interesting is that the movement that has begun to reinvigorate it was just
like what you said.
It was a handful of us really living the life and they gathered disciples around.
people.
like St. Joseph the Hezekast, for instance,
or St. Emiliano of Simonopatra,
who went and just lived, really lived the life
and then a group of gathers around them.
And then that reinbig rates.
It's not fundamentally about the forms
and the rules and the theories, right?
It's about the life, the actual life
of dedication to Christ in prayer.
And the other things flow out of that.
Right, right, and...
And we have to keep in mind what we read from Amos, right?
The part of the reason you don't find that theorizing is that this is a particular calling,
right?
This is not them laying out a pattern for all Christians of the way of salvation.
This is a particular calling for particular people, right?
The fact that St. Simeon's stylites lived on the pillar for years doesn't mean you should.
Yeah.
And we're not saying that.
We're not saying all the holiest people go and live out pillars.
No. Right.
There are these particular callings,
wherever particular people.
And these people are living out that calling.
And the judgment implied in that quotation from Amos,
by the way, still applies, as you were talking about,
monastic, they equip the people living within them
to follow God's calling on their life
or whether
they impede it, hinder it, leave them away from it, try to force them to stop, right?
Leave them in the opposite direction, right?
And so, when monastic settlements dwindle, when, quote, unquote, vocations are callings
to the priesthood dwindle. That is a
of a culture of a nation of communities that are improperly ordered.
Because it's not that God isn't putting that calling on anyone's life.
Yeah.
It's that something's stopping it from happening.
So the next, the next major figure who,
Compared to St. Anthony gets short-rift, but who I like talking about.
because not enough people know enough about him is St. John Cacheon. St. John Cacheon in the late
fourth and early fifth century, went everywhere, met everyone and did everything. He was from Scythia, he was from part of what's
now Romania. Yeah, or Dacia, I don't like all the also call it Dacia in that period. That's a different part, but yeah.
Oh.
Yeah. So he went and became a monk in Palestine and was given the name, his given name was
Cassianus, right? Roman name. He, he took the, received the name John when he was made
a monk for St. John the Forerunner. He got permission from his abbot at the monastery in Palestine
to go and visit a monastery.
Egypt. And then he and his friend, Germannus just stayed in Egypt and sort of overstayed their visa.
And while he was there, he wrote what was major works which is called the conferences, which is
him recording conversations he had with the desert fathers in the Egyptian desert while he was
there near the end of the century. When he left there eventually, they didn't want him back at
get the body serious Palestine because he'd oversee.
So he went to Constantinople and was ordained as a Deacon and was one of St. John
Christophe's Deacons. Specifically the Deacon in charge of Constantinople's church treasury.
When St. John Christophe was exiled, he was sent to Rome as a delegate to the Bishop of Rome to
try to get the Bishop of Rome to intervene to help St. John, who was the Bishop of Constantinople,
and exile. While there he met then Archdeacon Leo who later became St. Leo the Great.
the Pope of Rome and was commissioned to go and found the first monastery in Western Europe,
which he did, which is the monastery of St. Victor in Marseille, France.
And in the process of doing that, he wrote his other most well-known work, which is the
the Institute to the Monastic Life.
This is the other institute, sorry, Calvinist.
Institutes of the Minasic Life,
where he basically talks about the way things
were done in Palestine at that time.
The way things were done in Egypt at that time.
And compares those two and then talks about
how those practices could be adapted to Western Europe
where you have a very different climate,
very different situation in terms of being able
to grow food and what food you can grow
than the
Palestinian Desert or the Egyptian Desert.
Very different needs in terms of clothing.
He gets down to very practical things,
like being able to go barefoot or wear sandals
or footwear in the differences between the Egyptian Desert and France.
At this time.
He also in the context of those works, by the way,
has the eight evil thoughts which were eventually developed into the seven deadly sins,
Lexington, John Hessian did everything.
So, usually St. Benedict of Nersia sort of steals his thunder, the founder of Western
Minasticism, which is not the case, St. Benedict actually based his rule on St. John
Cations writings.
Yeah.
So, I mean, I think it's because his feast day is on February 29th, you know, so it's just
once, actually, we transferred to the 28th on Mon Leap years.
Yeah.
It's like our mutual friend, Father Joel, who...
is going to have his, I think, 13th birthday next year.
13th birthday. Good for him.
Well, he's 13 birthdays.
He got in some trouble in the West because of the Calvinists, but it was a bad rap, I tell you.
Oh, St. John, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, there's other fun facts like he is as far as we could tell the first
St. Ever canonized by a bishop of Rome.
Hey, there you go.
St. Gregory, the geologist, St. Gregory, the great had his relics taken and put in a silver
offer that said St. John Cashin on it.
Well, there's no arguing with that.
Yeah.
Oh, you'd be surprised.
Anyway.
Okay, there is arguing with that.
But it's foolish.
All of it.
So here's our, here we go.
Tied all together tonight.
Samson, not a Saint John Cashin.
Definitely a Saint.
Okay. Yes, indeed.
Yes.
So that's sort of our Egyptian monastic founder
are our European monastic founder.
Obviously, we be remiss as an orthodox.
podcast talking about monasticism did not talk about mad Athos. Yes. But because this is Lord
of Spirits we have to begin by pointing out that Athos was a giant. That's right. He was one of the
giants in the Greek Gigantomaki. Uh, he is supposed to be buried under Mount Athos. And mad
Athos itself is is was thought to be a rock that he threw at Poseidon. Yeah. Right. I've landed on
on them or whatever.
Yeah, Poseidon deflected it. He had a buried under his own rock hoisted by his own fatard
but so
Manathos the Great Christian monastic settlement is over the grave of a dead giant. Yeah, I mean and it's and for those of you who maybe don't know
It's a peninsula and the mountain itself is on the very southern end of it and there's actually there's a little chapel up there at the top now
I did not go
All the way up to the top of the mountain, but we were not that far from it. I went to Athos five years ago now
great, great experience. Yeah. Yeah. So now there is, right, the, the, we talk about the founding
of Mount Athos, right? So that fountain is usually pointed to a visit made, according to the history
maintained within the tradition of the church by the Theotokos to Mount Athos.
on her way with Saint John the Evangelist to Ephesus, where while they stopped there, she
prayed that her son, our God, would make it a garden dedicated revisionist about history
that it did not immediately become a monastic settlement.
Right. This was a prayer that was fulfilled later.
So because we know, right, there were still a mix of not only Christians and pagans living there, but Christian churches and pagan temples there, because Julie in the apostate, St. Constitutes nephew who took over for him as emperor ordered all the Christian churches there burned.
And then later on, St. P. Adiosius turned the tables and ordered all the
the pagan temples there burnt. That however we know did not actually happen because as
late as the fifth century, there was still a rather famous statue of Zeus there.
Yeah. Yeah. So yeah. Yeah. He wouldn't order. He wouldn't order pagan temples to be burned
if there weren't any there. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But but also right. It is worth noting.
The apostate did not just...
order all the Christian churches in the world burned down.
It was particular ones in particular places.
So that is actually really good historical evidence of the antiquity of the story of
the visit of the Theotokos there.
The fact that he was a special place.
So this was already seen as a play special which...
tells us that I think this is pretty good evidence that this story was already known
right in the early fourth century.
So yeah.
Yeah.
And there's some of the monasteries there.
Like I remember when we went to Vatopethi, they told us like the name of that monastery,
it refers grateful of getting us child back.
He endows this monastery there.
They in any event actually at Vatopethi, this is a connect us with our previous episode,
actually have
across or some significant fragment of the cross that Constantine carried into battle
at the Millivan Bridge. We were just sort of getting a tour and they pointed up behind
the altar and they said, oh, by the way, that's the cross that Constantine carried. And
I was like, oh, I didn't know we had that of Mount Athos into the monastic settlement
that it is today is Islam.
Hey
Did see that and see that one come and did you
specifically the Islamic conquest of North Africa.
Yes, so a bunch of refugees.
Yes, so there are a lot of Egyptian monks.
And it wasn't that there were already tons of organized monasteries there to receive them.
They just came and built a hut on Mount Athos.
And it's then later circa 8967 that St. Athanasius of Athos organizes things.
you
in something approaching the current organization.
Yeah, I mean, he basically takes what there is there and then has them all kind of working
together, rather than functioning as independent.
They are having this tradition tonight.
As we mentioned, there's this connection between the role of the monastic and the profit,
right, between the holy one who's pursued about the phenomenon of prophecy, but the connection
And there's that you have these people who are
outsiders who are outside of the general structure of the world of society, of
cultures of right and as people who are standing outside even to a certain extent
not completely in the case of monastics but to a certain extent outside of even
and Cherch hierarchy sometimes.
Can then critique, speak about, characterize, speak to, challenge.
right, culture, society, the church as a whole, right, culture, repentance. And they're
able to do that because of this status of being set apart and being separated from it.
But you can see that episode where we talk more about that. So the last thing we really
what I talk about is related to why a certain segment.
of, let's be honest, it's mostly our Protestant friends. Not all Protestants, but pretty close.
I know there's some Englican monasteries, but have sort of
jettison this tradition, this tradition starting with the Nazarites of the Old Covenant
coming through to Manasticism. And a lot of that really centers around starting even with
What Martin Luther has to say about monasticism centers around a misunderstanding of asceticism
What it is what works right what it's about what the purpose is
So Martin Luther for example sees it as
people either subjecting themselves to tortures or
Trying to do maritory things to try to earn salvation or earn forgiveness of their sins
may have been going through some people's minds, right? He may have been reflecting, well,
it goes, it is absolutely true if you've read any Martin Luther that he's reflecting on his own
experience, right? And his own set, as a man, right? Yeah, like I worked super hard to be saved,
and I'm not being saved. Yeah, in the Western, you know, I'm doing all this to try to experience
forgiveness, and I'm not experiencing forgiveness, right? So he's reflecting on his own thing.
Thank you.
But this is a misunderstanding of what the monastic tradition was originally about.
And a misunderstanding of what asceticism is about, that they very well have come up out in large parts of the West even before the Protestant Reformation.
So, one of the key elements that we have to remember with the setisism, whether we're talking
about the higher level of a setisism to which certain people are called in monasticism,
or just the asceticism that all Christians are called upon to practice, right?
It turns a fasting, etc. Right?
Is that asceticism is not giving up bad things.
Yeah.
You're supposed to give up bad that you're supposed to give up sin all the time.
Not just for lack.
Yeah.
Right.
It's like, well, for length, I'm going to sit in a little bit less.
And then I'll be back, you know, after they'll go back to do it.
All that sinful sounds is not asceticism.
Right.
It's like that.
That's just what you're supposed to do.
right? A cynicism is essentially giving up good things for better things. Yeah. Right? And what
that means is, and this is a place where we get Plato brain once again, right? Where Plato brain,
the good is always one. So if two things are differentiated, one must be better and the other one
one must be worse.
Yeah, or good or bad, right?
Yes.
And therefore...
Right? You get this, if you got that Plato brain infection still, right?
Then you look at the existence of celibate monastics and you say, oh,
someone who believes in in monasticism where people are celibate,
they must think marriage is bad. Right.
You could have two things that are both good, equally good for different people.
Yep.
The fact that we fast from meat, right?
Or any of the other things we fast from
in the Orthodox church in different periods like Lent,
doesn't mean that eating meat is bad.
Yeah, and you know, the funny thing is these things
aren't opposites, like marriage and celibacy
are not opposites because they're actually both chastity.
Just two different forms of chastity.
Yes.
There are different ways of life
to which different people are cold.
Yeah.
Right.
Right? And this is because, this is because asceticism is ultimately right when you're
talking about giving something up, when you're talking about offering something to God, you
don't offer God what is bad, you offer to God what is good. Right? So what does this mean?
And why would you do that? And what does it mean to give up something good for something better?
Well, to understand this, you have to sort of understand.
how humans work and how sin works.
And this is different than how we used to talk about.
We've talked about several times on the show I know
about the understanding of sin as the passions
that make us passive that act on us.
Well, the fathers make this distinction between
blameless passions and blameworthy passions.
So as humans, as humans who are finite beings,
finite created beings with material bodies.
etc. We suffer a lot of passions, right? Things act on us. Sloth, laziness, greed, anger, lust, pride,
right? These are blameworthy. These are sinful passions, right? It's not like there's a mean.
Well, you could be a little greedy, right? Just don't be too greedy, right? Sorry, Gordon Gecko.
right? You could be, you know,
a little lustful, but they'll go too far.
Right. No, these are blameworthy passions, right?
The blameless passions are the things that we suffer as humans that are not by their nature,
sinful. So for example, you get tired.
Right. I never sleep, but most people get tired. Right.
Um, there's nothing sinful about getting tired.
You get thirsty.
Right?
You have these things act upon you, right?
To get a little more advanced, right?
In order to get those things and live in the world, right?
You need to go out and you need to make a living.
You have to grow food or do something to get money to buy food, to support yourself and
your family, right?
There are things you have to do, things are finite lives in this world, right?
any of those
things, though they're not blameworthy, they're not sinful in and of themselves, can become
sinful if overindulged.
So if you overindulge your hunger, you become a glutton.
You eat far more than you need to, to stay alive.
You eat the wrong kind of stuff because it tastes good.
thing with sleep, right?
you go beyond the sleep and the rest that you need to laziness, right?
To I don't want to do anything ever if I can help it, right?
Which is a lot of teenagers, right?
No.
So, right?
And that's over and now it's become, it's entered into the realm of sin.
It's become blameworthy, even though it doesn't know if it's self-wasn't.
You take that need to go out and earn a living, support yourself, your family, you over
indulge that it becomes
pride in the pursuit of success. It becomes greed in the pursuit of wealth. And it turns into
as passions becoming blameworthy is a setisism. If we're talking about eating, turning into gluttony,
we have fasting. If we're talking about sleep, turning into laziness, we have vigils.
If we have the need to go out and provide for and support ourselves
into greed, we have the giving of alms to those in need. Right? We have these tools of asceticism
that keep those things from veering into sin as disciplines, as a pattern of the way of life. Right?
And so certain people are called to exercise and even sizing that higher level.
they glean certain things, they glean a certain perspective.
on the world, right?
Yes, indeed.
And is more able to see where the correct balance is and where it's becoming sinful than
I am who's in meshed in it, right?
And that's just one example, right?
You know, a person who is sort of always fasting to some extent, a monk I'm not Athos has
a very different relationship to food than I do.
surrounded by fast food joints, driving past 20 or 30 of them on the way home.
Right?
all wanting to sell me snacks.
You know, I have to say on that point, not about you and snacks.
I don't know about what you eat, but you don't want to trust me.
Well, I assume you get a lot of, a lot of crowd ads or crayfish.
I'm not sure where you call them.
Here's, here's, if I die before you, Father Andrew.
Okay.
I want you to make sure that they know that I am not a saint.
The reason my body is not decomposing is the preservatives.
8.
There we go.
Not holiness.
Well, you know, okay, this is gonna be
like a huge cemetery, this monastery is hundreds of years old,
but actually know it had like 12 graves in a total.
And the reason is that they of course recycle the graves.
They reuse them.
So, you know, among dies they put them in the ground.
And then later on they dig up his bones
and they put them in the osuere,
and then they reuse the grave.
And so the monk who is, we dig them up,
you know, put the bones in an osuere,
said now we leave them there as long.
as we can. And the reason is that because so many of the food items that we buy, you know,
they do grow some of their own food, but they also buy food too, have preservatives in
them. And so they leave the body in the earth as long as they can so that it has a longer
time to decompose because, like you said, food preservatives actually do prevent the body
from decomposing as quickly. The other thing that I'll relate with Manathos and eating
is that there is one of them
The it's called the Arkonvadi, which is where they sort of receive guests.
I can never remember if Arkonvadi is the person or the place.
Arkonvadi is the other word.
And there was this big painting there of a monk.
And he's got like all this, all this food he's stuffing into his, into
folds in his casick.
And it's all like coming out and falling out.
And you end.
and surrounding him.
It's really a crazy wild scary painting.
And it's labeled the secret eater,
which because you were mentioning about how monks
had an author, some of a very different relationship
to food.
Like, the painting really showed it like,
oh man, because the idea is that you eat it
meal times and that's it.
You don't sneak your own food.
You don't say, I'm feeling a little peccosh,
you know, I'm gonna go have a...
Yeah.
But yeah, I remember that.
We stepped in.
This is where they do hospitality.
And they're like, whoa.
That's a big...
Like the painting was like nine or 10 feet tall.
It was a big, a big painting.
Not an icon.
Just a very scary religious painting.
Yeah.
But so this is the key.
So this is the core difference between
the kind of asceticism that was practiced by stick groups
and the kind of asceticism that's practiced by Christianity.
The asceticism of Gnostic groups is based on the idea
that there are no...
goods in the world. Nothing in the created world is good. By virtue of being material,
by virtue of being created, it is evil. And therefore, it is to be avoided as much as
possible. And so you have this extremely rigorous asceticism, right? Brutal asceticism, right?
In in Gnostic circles. Christian asceticism is about not allowing the good things of God's
which we acknowledge are good, not letting them become bad,
not letting our own obsession with them,
our own yielding to our passions,
cause them to become a snare to us, right?
And preserving that balance.
That's the difference, and that is a major difference.
Yeah, that is not just a quantitative difference. That is a qualitative difference.
between the two. They're really two different things.
Yep. All right, well, to wrap up this episode on the Holy
Mystery of Monasticism, I wanted to say a few things about various bits that we've
kind of covered. One is, you know, most people, of course, and certainly the vast majority of people listening to this
are not monks or nuns and are probably not called to be monks or nuns.
Maybe handful of you out there maybe are.
So you might think, well, what does this have to do with me?
Well, certainly in the sense of being tortured as a monk or none, nothing.
If you're not going to live that life, then obviously that particular ritual you don't go through.
But that said, if you think about that Nazaridic vow
and you think about as seticism in general, as fathers
even just said, and to gain something better.
Right?
And I think that, especially, you know, we're here in the midst of great length, we're just
about halfway through, a little over halfway through now.
And it is a season, right?
It lasts a particular period.
And so it's, in some ways, it's like that Nisah right now, where it lasts for a particular
period.
And most of the time when people are engaging in the ascetical practices of...
of land, they're not thinking, well, I'm doing this for some particular purpose, you know,
aside from the purpose of preparing, purifying ourselves for a holy posse, which of course
is a pretty significant purpose.
But one can have multiple purposes at once.
And so I want to suggest this, and it doesn't matter that we're halfway through, you know,
you can start now.
But you know, when we have fasts, I think it's a good and appropriate thing to say, you know,
in conversation with your father, confessor, if it seems advisable to him, then to say,
I'm going to, as I engage in the normal practices of great length under his guidance, I'm going to
dedicate it to praying for this person or for this purpose, to aim our asceticism particularly at that.
Again, it doesn't
anything, right? It doesn't earn anything. Ultimately, it's about drawing close to Christ. But as we purify
ourselves, our prayers become more effective, not because God says, well, if you just turn up the
volume a little bit on this, that I'm going to hear you. No, that's not what that means. It's really
that we become more receptive to the grace of God by doing this. Right, it's not automatic, but...
it's part of the whole package of a life of prayer.
Related to that, right, is,
you know, I mentioned that I got to go to Mount Athos
and one of the most beautiful experiences of my life
and if you know me, you know, I like to go on pilgrimage,
not just because Jeffrey Chaucer,
although April is coming.
I love to go on pilgrimage.
And of course, you know, Orthodox Christian pilgrimage
is often included in the system.
monasteries, but not always. It could be other holy places. The Greek word for pilgrimage
is proskinaima, which means veneration. So you go to venerate, right? And, you know,
Father Stephen and I had a conversation the other day, and we talked a little bit about
pilgrimage and he made the point. And of course, it's a very good point that there's nothing
sort of available on pilgrimage that isn't available at your local parish. Right? It's
not like if I go to Mount Athos and receive Holy Communion there that it's sort of better
community.
that it is here in Emmaus, Pennsylvania, and Lafayette Louisiana, or wherever you live,
listener, it's not. It's the same Christ that in stepping outside of our normal day-to-day
life, we become more receptive. If done well, pilgrimage is not just going on a vacation,
or it's not a vacation, or even just going on a trip. It's about orienting ourselves towards
the veneration of what is holy to receive the grace of
God. And so if we do that, then we can become more receptive within the scope of this
frame of time that the pilgrimage takes. So again, it's like that old Nazareth Vow that
can be temporary. And so we set aside this time in order to give it to God so that we can
receive something and bring it back home. You know, it's one of the things that was told
to me when I was on my notes. I just suddenly had this thought, which I just said out loud.
Thank you.
And which is not generally a good thing to do in a monastery, just to say your thoughts out loud.
But I did nonetheless, we were being given a tour by one of the monks at the monastery we were at.
And I said, you know, I suddenly feel sad for all the people that I know that would so much love to be here.
You know, there I was on the Holy Mountain.
And he said to me, well, God has sent you here.
And he didn't mean just me, but the other people with me.
He sent you here so that you can bring home...
what you received here. So you have a responsibility to the people where you live to give them what you're getting here. That's your responsibility.
And the engagement that we have with asceticism, the engagement that we have with periods like Ren with Great Lent, it is precisely to serve this purpose of love ultimately.
Ultimately, it's not a private.
spiritual experience. It's because, I mean, as the scripture says, if I have all these
other glorious gifts but have not loved, I'm nothing. I'm nothing. Right? And so fundamentally,
a monastic is should be one of the most loving people that there is. We tend to think of them
is utterly separated from the world, but that's not really true.
Of course,
they have the Ministry of Hospitality that they give, but also their prayers that they offer
for the world which are so needed, but then also the spiritual counsel, the advice, the experience
that they give to those who come to them. It's invaluable, invaluable. Right. And so when we encounter
people who are living this more intensified manner of ascetical living, then we can receive some of
something like that.
from them, but also then when we ourselves take on maybe just the tiny little bit that
we're able for a brief period of time, then that needs to be some something that's offered
to other people.
Not that I say, well, you know, I fasted on Wednesday and Friday this week and that makes
me a wise person who needs to give counsel to everybody.
No, that's not what I mean.
But it should make us serve our fellow men and women.
And if we're not doing that, then we're kind of not doing it right.
If we're not actually becoming more loving, then we're not doing it right.
we're doing something else.
And so that's kind of the collection of thoughts
that I have about all the things
that we've just been discussing.
So Father Stephen,
I'm after briefly, I'm actually you.
Oh, go for it.
Lafayette Louisiana has the best of everything.
Oh, excuse me, well, you'll have to show me some time.
So, yes, but beyond that,
So what I want to talk about here at the end is built off of something I was trying to emphasize,
like when it came to St. John the Forerunner and St. Anthony the Great, the idea of
embodying something with the life we live, doing something by living a certain way.
So
If you've studied philosophy a little bit, like most of them on the internet, most of them lie to you.
Most of them have completely misinformed you about how ancient philosophy works, worked.
Right? What it was about.
Because philosophy was not about ideas in the ancient world.
And by any means, but almost everyone I've ever seen in every
Trotofilosophy textbook,
treats ancient philosophy as a bunch of talking heads
who come up with different ideas.
In actuality, ancient philosophy was a way of life.
Diogenes practiced a way of life and being in the world.
Socrates practiced a way of life and being in the world.
The academy, the platenists,
had a way of life and being in the world,
the stoics, the Epicurians.
Aristotle had a way of life and being in the world
this parapetetic.
school. That's what it was about. Right. And the ideas arose and the ideas came to be framed out of
an around that way of life, but it was a way of life and a way of being. And the reason we've
been taught philosophy the wrong way is that for the most part we've come to understand Christianity the
the wrong way. We've come to understand Christianity and specifically Christian theology as...
bunch of talking heads who came up with ideas and are exchanging those ideas, which of these
ideas are correct and which ones are wrong. And how do we discriminate between them and
what kind of arguments are in court and ruled out of court and how does that all work?
And that's not how Christianity works. It's not ever been how Christianity actually works.
Christianity is a way of life and a way of being
in the world. And what it originally meant to be a Christian was to follow that way of
life and that way of being. And so it wasn't like today where you just where we've sunk
in past just I am X because I believe XYZ to be true. Now it's I am X because I have
chosen to identify today as X.
And...
That's often coupled with in our sort of post-structuralist, post-modern world, with the idea
that who I am is a story that I tell myself.
I have this story I tell myself that's based on me taking events I remember from my
life and casting them in a certain way, to turn it into a story, into a single narrative
line that brings me from some point in my past to today.
tell that story, that's who I am.
Here's the problem with that.
Tomorrow, I can come up with another story
with a different end result
and therefore with a different identity for myself.
And I don't even have to lie to myself to do it,
even though we all lie to ourselves
to varying degrees all the time
about who we are and our pasts and what we do,
to radically different stories about who I am
by what details and what story
of my past, I choose to tell and how I choose to string those those details together. I can not
consciously lie and be present myself as two completely different people because none of those are who I am.
None of those stories. Who I am is who I am today, who I am when you meet me, when you talk to me,
that's who I am. And it's defined by a bunch of relationships between me and
people in the world and roles that I play and connections that I have and duties
and responsibilities that I have and either fulfill or fail to fulfill. That's who I am and
that's located within a tradition and a way of being that you can describe as Orthodox Christian.
Right and and and that's who I am. And so my goal is an Orthodox Christian then and as a priest is
to from day to day.
embody that identity by living and being that way in the world in terms of
the responsibilities and relationships that entails and all of those things as
I move forward. And part of the problem I think for us as modern people in
understanding monasticism, Christian monasticism, is that Christian
an astrosism as we saw tonight, I think, is so obviously just a
way of life, just here in scare quotes, right? So obviously a way of life and a way of being.
So obviously not about a bunch of ideas I have in my head, right? When you meet a Christian
monastic, one who's established in the monastic life, right? And you're trying to determine who
that monk is there's no story that he he tells himself right.
who he is is a monk, who he is is in a body embodiment of this way of life. And so coming
from our perspective where we have this kind of protean self that can be defined and redefined,
we don't know how to deal with something that's obviously so foreign. But once we come
to understand, and I can only speak from the perspective, isn't even just obedience to
certain things but
a way of being in the world, you understand that monasticism is only in this case quantitatively
different, not qualitatively different from the life of any Orthodox Christian. That a Christian
monastic is embodying within themselves the Orthodox Christian way of life and way of being in the
world.
just in a more deep and more full way than I probably am most of the time.
That's not that's because the Orthodox Christian monastic has dedicated themselves and their
entire life to living that out.
And I still like the Israelites who were onlookers on Mount Carmel and hovering between two opinions.
I still, on the one hand, there is a part of me that wants nothing more than to be an Orthodox priest and an Orthodox Christian, and to embody that in the world and to find salvation through that.
There's another part of me that wants to be a cool guy that wants to be, that wants to follow the things that interest me in culture, the things that I think...
are fun and enjoyable that wants to embody something very different,
some particular nerdy corner of American culture.
And this isn't to say, right, that any of those things are bad.
See the distinction we made about asceticism.
But when the rubber meets the road
and I decide to spend how I spend my time and how I spend my money and where I place
my attention and where I place my affections.
Those things that are not evil in and of themselves can become that in my life because they can
pull me away from who I really ought to be.
And so asceticism as we practice it in Lent is really a call for all of us.
me included. Focus our attention, our efforts, our doing and our being toward who we are in Christ,
who we've already been made in Christ and who are called to be in Christ,
and away from all those other things competing to be embodied in and through us.
And so if we want to have a successful length.
That is exactly what what we need to do most of all beyond following fasting rules
beyond service of
The life in Christ that were called to be and do in the world
Amen
Amen. Well, that is our show for tonight. Thank you very much everyone for listening
If you didn't happen to call us live, we'd still like to hear from you
you can email us at Lord of Spirits, ancient faith.com.
You can send us a message at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voice message and speak pipe dot com slash Lord of spirits
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific
Maybe not this next next month it might go weird places and go joy
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page join our discussion group
Libreviews ratings wherever
Appropriates most importantly share the show with a friend that is going to benefit from it.
and leave some reviews and inappropriate places to them.
Hey!
And finally, be sure to go to www.AxRank.com.spokesupport
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air.
You can stay all day if you want.
Thank you. Good night. God bless you.
You've been listening.
to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young,
a listener supported.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands,
saying with a lot and wisdom and strength
and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter five verses 11 through 12.
Welcome to Eastern Christian Insights with Father Philip Lamasters.